<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Cathy Wise</title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://cathywise.net/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net" />
<updated>2024-11-23T09:30:30+11:00</updated>
<id>https://cathywise.net/</id>
<author>
  <name>Cathy Wise</name>
  <uri>https://cathywise.net/</uri>
  <email></email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2024/11/23/2024-11-22-prior-prior-purl.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2024/11/23/2024-11-22-prior-prior-purl</id>
  <published>2024-11-23T09:30:30+11:00</published>
  <updated>2024-11-23T09:30:30+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 1957 the Fairfield Sewing Machine Centre in Sydney posted &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189945409&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189940098&quot;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189933781&quot;&gt;series&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189946111&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189946579&quot;&gt;newspaper&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189947315&quot;&gt;ads&lt;/a&gt; for the Prior Purl knitting machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/prior/nla.news-page21534534-nla.news-article189939634.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Newspaper advertisment for the Prior Purl knitting machine. It's a poor quality photo copy, but it does show a picture of someone using the machine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1957 ‘Advertising’, The Biz (Fairfield, NSW : 1928 - 1972), 24 July, p. 23. , viewed 22 Nov 2024, http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article189939634&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South Australia, one further ad was placed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article267057263&quot;&gt;“Trudgen’s”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, there’s a slow trickle of Prior Purl machines mentioned in the classifieds sections of various newspapers. Even now, occasionally one turns up on a local marketplace or website for sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s special about the Prior Purl? The world is awash with old knitting machines, most by much better known brands. But the Prior Purl is a &lt;em&gt;garter stitch&lt;/em&gt; machine, and it was made in Australia. Both of those are highly unusual, making this machine an unsual item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A garter stitch machine looks kind of like any other double-bed machine (such as a Passap), but rather than having two beds of needles, it has one set of double-ended needles it passes back and forth. So to knit garter stitch, or seed stitch, or any other purl-textured pattern, you just have to move the needles to the appropriate possition and pass the carriage. You don’t need to manually transfer any stitches. You can see that in action in this video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=voNiqdCXtTY&quot;&gt;Prior Purl does Garter Stitch by Nix Knits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garter stitch can be accieved on a standard machine by &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uo_H0f4NzXY?t=236&quot;&gt;using a garter bar and flipping the entire work after each row&lt;/a&gt;. But something like seed stitch requires &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/2UUkWcaPshw?t=368&quot;&gt;manual stitch manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/PzkgDfeEYDA&quot;&gt;Brother Garter Carriage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So hopefully you can see why, when I saw one recently for $10, I jumped on it. For that price, it would be interesting even if it was mostly rust, and it didn’t look to be too rusty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve begun the process of cleaning it and making it nice. I asked around if anyone had more on this machine, and was pointed to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.knittingmachinemuseum.com/prior-purl-machine&quot;&gt;Prior Purl Knitting Machhine&lt;/a&gt; as the Knitting Machine Museum. This one looks different to mine, with a golden needle bed and knob handles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1jAuSM_PyiM&quot;&gt;Deep Cleaning a Prior Plain’n Purl with Bakelite [sic] beds&lt;/a&gt; by Akeru Joyden (Rumpledsilkskeins) on Youtube. This looks exactly like mine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ravelry.com/discuss/machine-knitting/3842417&quot;&gt;Prior Purl ‘n Plain Garter Machine Ravelry thread&lt;/a&gt; (login required) which recommends against the technique in the above video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already made one mistake with the cleaning, I left some of the spare needles in white vinegar for too long and disolved the pins! This is especially sad as these are a more unusual needle and may be hard (or impossible) to replace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning a trip to the National Library to access &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalogue.nla.gov.au/catalog?q=%22Priors+Pty.+Ltd%22&amp;amp;search_field=author&quot;&gt;their copies of the manuals and books&lt;/a&gt; which will hopefully be enlightening. The manuals aren’t available online, and since the Library believes they are still in copyright, they won’t be putting them in the digital collection yet. Hopefully some day!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2024/11/23/2024-11-22-prior-prior-purl.html&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on November 23, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toy Story - Nintendo Knitting Machine]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2024/06/04/nintendo-knitting.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2024/06/04/nintendo-knitting</id>
  <published>2024-06-04T06:00:00+10:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-04T06:00:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/knitting/ad.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Now You're Knitting With Power - advertisment showing a knitting machine with partially-worked knitting, a CRT TV showing some kind of guide or instructions, and a Nintendo Entertainment System&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/share/3RFTcuPPjZAfj1A5/?mibextid=WC7FNe&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard of the Nintendo Knitting Machine in a Machine Knitting discord where it was described as the truly unobtainable knitting machine. This is probably true, we only know of the existence of one unit, which “Gamemaster” Howard Phillips &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/share/SACYZJpLeBADzVzH/?mibextid=WC7FNe&quot;&gt;demonstrated in the late 1980s&lt;/a&gt;, and which was advertised in a trade magazine above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was intrigued. Even from this one image we can see a few notable things about this knitting machine. 
First, it appears to be plastic. That’s not surprising, the plastic bed Silver Reed LK100 &lt;a href=&quot;https://s917320818ade283a.jimcontent.com/download/version/1534837163/module/10654462579/name/%E7%B7%A8%E6%A9%9F%E5%B9%B4%E8%A1%A8.pdf&quot;&gt;came out in 1985&lt;/a&gt; and the first Bond &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/cashinginonneedl0000curr/page/34/mode/2up?q=Bond+&quot;&gt;machines came out in 1981&lt;/a&gt;. But if you look closer at the picture, it’s not just the bed that is plastic, it’s also the needles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plastic needles are most commonly seen today in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WrNYn_7WJMU&quot;&gt;Sentro&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wdz5dUsPxnc&quot;&gt;Addi&lt;/a&gt; circular knitting machines. But when I realised it had plastic needles, I wondered if that meant it was made by a toy manufacturer, rather than one of Japan’s established knitting machine manufacturers (like Brother, Toyota, or Silver Reed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still sometimes get toy knitting machines in Japan, both circular and flat. Bandai made &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bandai.co.jp/catalog/item.php?jan_cd=4902425627762000&quot;&gt;a Pingu one&lt;/a&gt; and Takara Tomy has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.takaratomy.co.jp/products/amukawaamina/&quot;&gt;one covered in bows&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a7Pg6SXNmD4&quot;&gt;one with “patterning”&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe whoever made this machine ended up just selling the machine on its own in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also had a hunch that the maker of this machine might be a company Nintendo already had a relationship with. Maybe even one who had made some kind of Famicom software released before or after this collab. I did a check of the NES software catalogue, and found some knitting software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Famicom Disk System actually had two pieces of knitting software. “I am a teacher: Knitting Fundamentals” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gamingalexandria.com/highquality/fds/I%20Am%20a%20Teacher%20-%20Teami%20no%20Kiso/I%20Am%20a%20Teacher%20-%20Teami%20no%20Kiso.pdf&quot;&gt;アイアムアティーチャー あみのきそ&lt;/a&gt;, September 1986) and “I am a teacher: Super Mario’s Sweater” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://wikiwiki.jp/vipgt6/%E3%82%A2%E3%82%A4%E3%82%A2%E3%83%A0%E3%82%A2%E3%83%86%E3%82%A3%E3%83%BC%E3%83%81%E3%83%A3%E3%83%BC%20%E3%82%B9%E3%83%BC%E3%83%91%E3%83%BC%E3%83%9E%E3%83%AA%E3%82%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%82%BB%E3%83%BC%E3%82%BF%E3%83%BC/%E6%89%8B%E3%81%82%E3%81%BF%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8D%E3%81%9D&quot;&gt;アイアムアティーチャー　スーパーマリオのセーター&lt;/a&gt;, August 1986). The former &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dFaZaE5qhMw&quot;&gt;(attempts)&lt;/a&gt; to teach you knitting (the manual is more useful than the software on this front). The latter is a knitting pattern generator for some jumpers with stranded colourwork and intarsia designs for Mario-and-Friends. Both of these titles were made by a company called “Royal”. That name struck a memory feeling, and looking them up I remembered Royal also made knitting accessories like yarn ball winders. A likely target!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then while browsing through auction sites for toy knitting machines, and products by Royal, I saw it. The Royal Knit System (ロイヤルニットシステム).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/knitting/knitting-machine.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Knit System machine&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://page.auctions.yahoo.co.jp/jp/auction/q1087052620&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/knitting/knitting-machine-closeup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Knit System machine - closeup of side of bed showing 25 needle count (per side)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://page.auctions.yahoo.co.jp/jp/auction/q1087052620&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/knitting/knitting-machine-boxed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Knit System with pink carriage, in box with various packaging and VHS&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://aucview.com/yahoo/f106900482/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handle and stickers are a little different, and the Nintendo machine is 60 stitches rather than 50, but otherwise it’s exactly what we’re looking for. It’s a toy knitting machine with plastic needles, in two different colours, in sets of four. It even has the little window in the carriage so you can see the needles knit. And with these extra pictures you can see that the plastic needles aren’t like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://addi.de/en/product-2/addiei-replacement-needles-2/&quot;&gt;ones for circular machines&lt;/a&gt; they’re actually latch-hook needles &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewoolendiva.weebly.com/mk-70-needle-comparison-chart.html&quot;&gt;like the metal ones other flat-bed machines use&lt;/a&gt;. Facinating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does the machine attach to the Nintendo? You can see in the picture that the Nintendo controller is held in a bracket on the machine, in much the same way &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.sckmcl.com.hk/products/row-counter-knitting-machine-singer-silver-sk280-sk270-07302003?_pos=11&amp;amp;_sid=a31799c7f&amp;amp;_ss=r&quot;&gt;a row counter might&lt;/a&gt; (it looks to me like the’ve kind of jammed it in to a row counter holder). If you look closely, you can see it’s positioned so that when the carriage goes past, it’ll hit a tab, which will hit the A button on the controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve tried either of the Famicom software titles things might click into place about now. When going through a sweater design in that software it takes you through row by row starting at the bottom, and working in flat piece. Just like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wickedwoollies.home.blog/tag/knitradar/&quot;&gt;charting device for a knitting machine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all this “connection” is, I think, is the carriage hitting the A button on the controller to advance the pattern instructions on the screen. Sorry to disappoint anyone looking for something as cool as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://shonumi.github.io/articles/art22.html&quot;&gt;Gameboy sewing machines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think you could round up the parts to make your own Nintendo Knitting Machine. You just need to find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Knitting System ~ ¥3,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A copy of Super Mario Sweater ~ ¥3,000 (if you can find one, and more if you want it with the box)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Famicom + Disk System ~ ¥5,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A TV that can take NTSC input from the Famicom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something to hold your controller so the carriage hits the A button when it goes past&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it! A Famicom Knitting Machine.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2024/06/04/nintendo-knitting.html&quot;&gt;Toy Story - Nintendo Knitting Machine&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on June 04, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Weekend With Nokia 3 & Android Pie]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2020/05/04/android.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2020/05/04/android</id>
  <published>2020-05-04T06:00:00+10:00</published>
  <updated>2020-05-04T06:00:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Friday I took my iPhone 8 in to an authorised repairer to get a new battery. I’ll get it back on Monday, but I’m spending the weekend with a Nokia 3 running Android Pie, or as it is known in our house, The Punishment Phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phone is very, very slow. Watching it draw the UI feels like pages loading on dialup. I feel this makes it “unfair” to judge it but instead I’ll judge it all the more. Don’t want to be judged for making slow phones Nokia? Don’t make slow phones. This isn’t some carrier-branded $39 toy phone, it should work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only downloaded and installed the minimum I thought I would need to get by, given that I’ll still have my iPad. I installed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apple Music&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Line / Line lite&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instagram&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snapchat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also signed in so I got GMail and Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I didn’t install and I miss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tuner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Piano controller app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-like&quot;&gt;Things I like&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found a way to increase the UI density from Spaced Out to normal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have an analogue clock widget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-dont-like&quot;&gt;Things I don’t like&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jittery, laggy, garbage slow scrolling in every app but especially Chrome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slow notifications for emails&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keyboard is slow to come up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes I get upset with how slow it is and mash buttons and that makes it worse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I hate capacitive buttons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I keep trying to do iPhone X gestures to navigate even though I’ve never owned an iPhone X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to edge swipe to go back or up a nav level but it opens the drawer I never want the drawer go away drawer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;None of the apps I installed have wigets that work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The clock wiget doesn’t have numbers and I can’t work out how to change that or if it’s impossible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-dont-like-that-arent-android-or-nokias-fault&quot;&gt;Things I don’t like that aren’t Android or Nokia’s fault&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can’t log into Line or Line Lite because my iPhone is in the repair shop so I can’t get a confirmation code and I don’t want to log my iPhone out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2020/05/04/android.html&quot;&gt;A Weekend With Nokia 3 & Android Pie&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Washi Tape Photo Corners]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2019/10/09/washi-tape-photo-corners.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2019/10/09/washi-tape-photo-corners</id>
  <published>2019-10-09T00:00:00+11:00</published>
  <updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I used to have a box of commercial photo corners, clear ones like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.officeworks.com.au/shop/officeworks/p/lifestyle-brands-photo-corners-clear-250-pack-ur80820&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; that I found somewhere in my parent’s stationery and, um, adopted. I use them in scrapbooking to hold down photos. I know I could just glue the photos in, or tape the photos down, and I sometimes do. But most of the time I like to be able to take the photos out in future and not have a sticky mess on them. I also use them to hold in things where I’m not sure the glue will stick, like plastic tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran out of photo corners while in Japan and I could not find them anywhere. After much searching I found a tutorial for &lt;a href=&quot;https://chihirolifememo.net/maste_cornarseal/&quot;&gt;making photo corners from washi tape&lt;/a&gt; (Japanese). After much practice I think I’ve improved the technique a little bit so I thought it was worth expanding on and making available in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you’ll need is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/washi_tape&quot;&gt;washi tape&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. These days washi tape is available just about anywhere, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kmart.com.au/product/washi-tape-10-pack-timeless/2371837&quot;&gt;Kmart&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ikea.com/au/en/catalog/products/50338400/&quot;&gt;IKEA&lt;/a&gt; so you shouldn’t have any trouble finding it. This technique also uses the most common kind of washi tape, 15mm wide tape in a simple design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/tapes.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Different kinds of washi tape. Cutout tape, 6mm wide tape, 30mm wide tape, 15mm wide tape with simple designs, 15mm wide tape with complex designs, washi tape stickers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique won’t work with fancy tape with a cutout shape, the 6mm (or thinner!) tape, washi tape stickers, or tape with complex designs. You can use wider tapes like 30mm, but this will make very large corners. Very large corners might be useful for holding booklets, but since I’m mostly using Instax mini, I use the standard 15mm tape to make photo corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to illustrate this tutorial using a tape with a design of a ruler marked in centimetres, which is very handy for showing how to do this and how much tape is used. I wouldn’t usually use this design because large designs like this are lost in the tiny photo corner. I’d usually recommend a tape with a simple design (stripes, diamonds) or plain colours. Save your cute character tapes for borders or backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Scissors, 15mm washi tape, an Instax mini photo, a grey scrapbooking page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what you need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scissors, a tape cutter, a knife, or really good tearing skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;15mm washi tape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something you want to stick down, like a photo or ticket&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something you want to stick it to, like a scrapbook album page or a greeting card&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;5cm of washi tape peeled off the roll&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the end of your tape and peel off about 5cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;1cm down from the end of the tape, there is a fold in the tape. On the inside is a 90º angle and on the outside there are two 135º angles, like when a corner is cut off a square&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving 1cm&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of tail, with sticky sides together, fold the tape so it goes at 90º to where it was before. It should have a cut-off sort of corner, with two 135º angles on the outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;1cm down from the end of the tape, there is a fold in the tape. On the outside there is a 135º angle, then a 90º angle, then another 135º angle so that the tape goes back the way it came from leaving a point&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fold again, sticky sides together. The tail and the part attached to the roll should have the sticky sides facing the same way, and there should be a 90º corner on the tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;As above, but the tape is up the other way with the sticky side up&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turn the tape so the sticky side faces up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;1cm down from the end of the tape, there is a fold in the tape. From the end of the tape, with sticky side up, going along the left edge: 1cm straight, 90º angle, 15mm (width of tape) along, 90º angle, straight to roll. Going along the right edge: 1cm straight, 135º angle, ~21mm, 225º angle, straight to roll.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fold the part attached to the roll down as far as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The two halves are being folded together like closing a book, with the left side on top of the right.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fold down the middle, as if closing a book (a vertical valley fold).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Sticky side of the tape is facing up. The end of the tape is at the top, the roll is at the bottom. There is 1cm of sticky side, then a triangle of not-sticky, then sticky side is up all the way&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turn it over so the sticky side faces up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A triangle has been cut off the end of the left edge of the end of the tape. Going up the right-hand side of the tape, from the roll there are: a few cm of sticky side, 15mm of not-sticky side, 1cm of sticky side. Going up the left-hand side, there are a few cm of sticky side, and then the point of the not-sticky triangle, and then the end of the tape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut off the end of the tape on an angle, to mirror the non-sticky triangle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The triangle at the end of the tape has been folded down towards the viewer, over the non-sticky triangle, it does not match exactly.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fold the end down towards you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/step-13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The work has been cut from the roll and turned sticky side down. It now has a triangular pocket facing up&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut the tape straight across under the triangle. You should then have a sticky triangle and a not-sticky triangle. If you turn it over, you will have a little pocket. I used 5.5cm of tape to make this photo corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/scrapbook-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A page from a scrapbook with 6 Instax mini photos. From top left, a print has photo corners on two corners, a print has photo corners on two corners, a print is held down by tape on four sides, a print has photo corners on two corners, two prints are taped by tape on three sides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can use your photo corner! I generally use two on opposite corners to hold down an Instax mini print, which is 54mm by 86mm. I would recommend four to hold down a 4” by 6” photo print. Make sure to press firmly over the sticky bit, which isn’t under the bit that goes over the photo. You will have to touch the photo, sorry… maybe use a tissue over your finger if you’re worried about oils from your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/photo-corners/scrapbook-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A page from a photo album. All six photos are held in with washi tape photo corners&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Confusingly, washi tape is not made of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washi&quot;&gt;washi&lt;/a&gt;, a type of Japanese paper. In Japan it’s known simply as masking tape (マスキングテープ). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you would like to be a perfectionist you can leave 1.5cm at the end and it will look neater on the back, but nobody can see the back so I save 0.5cm of tape and just use 1cm. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2019/10/09/washi-tape-photo-corners.html&quot;&gt;Washi Tape Photo Corners&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on October 09, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seven Mistakes Every Programmer Should Make]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2019/06/22/mistakes-for-all.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2019/06/22/mistakes-for-all</id>
  <published>2019-06-22T00:00:00+10:00</published>
  <updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lots of people are willing to tell you things you “have to learn” before you start seriously programming, but I find that I learn best by just making mistakes. So here’s seven mistakes you should make once you start programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-gently-abuse-a-scripting-language&quot;&gt;1. (Gently) Abuse a Scripting Language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered what people mean by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.python.org/moin/GlobalInterpreterLock&quot;&gt;GIL in Python&lt;/a&gt;? Why not find out first-hand! You could also try running a data-processing heavy Rails server, or why not try out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wxperl.it&quot;&gt;wxPerl&lt;/a&gt; for your next desktop app. Any use of PHP also checks this item off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-run-out-of-memory-in-the-jvm&quot;&gt;2. Run Out of Memory in the JVM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There must be some programmers out there (bless them) that don’t ever need to use the JVM, but for most of us at some point we’ll be writing Java, or maybe Kotlin or Clojure. Since the JVM can be a bit of a memory monster it’s not hard to make a mistake and run through the default amount of memory on your system. Then you get to watch the computer grind like crazy trying to do garbage collection. Bonus points if you’re running test/CI on a really small cloud instance so it works fine in dev and just falls over in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-drop-the-database-unexpectedly&quot;&gt;3. Drop the Database Unexpectedly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you really mean to drop the database, but it’s always fun to drop it when you were trying to do something else. A classic way to do this is to copy-paste the wrong SQL block against a live database, but hey it’s up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-abuse-the-main-thread&quot;&gt;4. Abuse the Main Thread&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can’t quite get your head around threading? Just use the main thread! Bonus points if the “main” thread is the UI thread in a native application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-do-something-nasty-in-javascript&quot;&gt;5. Do Something Nasty in JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s so &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; ways to do terrible things in JavaScript that this almost feels like a cheat, but the trick with this one is to do something that works but will be baffling to any future developers (including yourself). The classic would be using a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;==&lt;/code&gt; (not &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;||&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;===&lt;/code&gt;) and really meaning it; you could also try deleting variables or anything else a good linter might take exception to. Bonus points here if you managed to redefine &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;undefined&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://kangax.github.io/compat-table/es5/#test-Immutable_undefined&quot;&gt;back in IE8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-think-youve-found-a-compiler-or-interpreter-bug&quot;&gt;6. Think You’ve Found a Compiler or Interpreter Bug&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually you’ll find an actual bug in a compiler or interpreter you use a lot (there’s only a small chance it will be unknown). But long before that you’ll &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; you’ve found a bug, probably when you’ve just done something really silly. If you’re unlucky you’ll post this in a bug tracker or mailing list and get a massive eyeroll from the maintainers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-write-something-that-takes-forever-to-run&quot;&gt;7. Write Something That Takes Forever to Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This usually happens when you’re in a hurry and you realise the computer doesn’t get weekends. This is hopefully a simple thing like some log analysis script and not a scary mistake like running a script that in-place updates the production DB while other people are using it and you’re in bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-probably-okay&quot;&gt;It’s (Probably) Okay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re never going to stop making mistakes. I get annoyed with my old work at least every other day, but really beating yourself up over it isn’t going to help. Try and be as constructive as you can when you make mistakes. For small mistakes, it’s often enough to make a mental note and move on. For larger mistakes, look out for structural problems that are behind your mistake. Would it be helpful to get things like this reviewed by more people in future? Did I just grab the complete wrong end of the stick because I didn’t ask enough questions? Can I write some automated tests to prevent this? Can I turn on a linter or compiler feature that will warn me? Can I spin up a duplicate environment to check this on instead of the main test environment? Even something simple like “don’t merge into the master branch just before leaving for the day”.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2019/06/22/mistakes-for-all.html&quot;&gt;Seven Mistakes Every Programmer Should Make&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on June 22, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two Cameras]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2018/06/12/two-cameras.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2018/06/12/two-cameras</id>
  <published>2018-06-12T00:00:00+10:00</published>
  <updated>2018-06-12T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently inherited two cameras from my maternal grandparents. One was my grandmother’s, the other my grandfather’s. Both of them are fascinating as objects in their own right, but I also find them interesting for what they say about my grandparents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/pair.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kodak Instamatic Pocket 100 in original plastic box in front of a light brown leather camera bag with zip-around top and front buckled pocket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be able to tell from the picture what the first camera is, but I’ve kept the second wrapped up in its lovely vintage leather bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/instamatic.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kodak Instamatic Pocket 100 in original plastic box. Box top is clear, box base is black with a red plastic insert that holds the camera components. Manual is on table in front of box, has a picture of a young woman holding the camera up to her eye&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting at the front, it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instamatic&quot;&gt;Kodak Instamatic Pocket 100&lt;/a&gt;, which was Grandma’s camera. It was probably the best camera you could get for her, although evidence would suggest she only used one roll of film before putting the camera away and never using it again. I guess Grandma wasn’t really into photography, even though the Instamatic Pocket was the camera for people who didn’t like cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/instamatic-body.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of Instamatic showing Kodak name on the front, flash attachment slot and shutter button. Top has a metallic finish, camera is otherwise black plastic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you see any wheel or controls at all? There’s one button on the top for the shutter. You do have to remember to open the lens cover, but everything else is preset. The little cassettes of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/110_film&quot;&gt;110 film&lt;/a&gt; even had a window where you could see how many frames you had left in the roll. It has a viewfinder to the left, which is going to have terrible parallax issues, but who cares! This is a camera for family snaps in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera comes with instructions, but they’re really just how to open the film door. It’s a single sheet in six languages. If you don’t want to read a manual (and Grandma never did) then this is the camera for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/magicube.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Magicube flash unit with four single-use flash bulbs. Attached to camera directly or with provided extension pole. Magicube is small and silver with a clear plastic cover, two boxes of Magicubes are shown in the background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also used these cute &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flash_(photography)#flashcube&quot;&gt;magicubes&lt;/a&gt;, which are pretty sweet until you realise all the safety warnings are because they’re a tiny explosion. Science! One came packaged with the camera, and I also received two boxes of flashes, in total 6 although at least one has been used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also this ridiculous “red eye reduction” solution of a plastic tower to put the flash cube on. I guess if the subject were close it would move the light out of the plane of the lens so you’d get less reflection on the subject’s retinas? I don’t want to stand that close to a magicube when it goes off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/aires.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A group of camera equipment in front of a leather camera bag. Including a camera in a full leather case, a leather lens box, a light meter, some film canisters, and a manual&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perfect fodder for my vintage love. This darling is an &lt;a href=&quot;http://camerapedia.wikia.com/wiki/Aires_Viscount&quot;&gt;Aires Viscount&lt;/a&gt; and comes with a leather half case and leather front cover with chrome accents both of which are lined with orange velvet. The telephoto lens attachement also comes in a leather box lined with orange velvet. Did I mention the camera bag is lined with purple velvet? My modern camera came in a cardboard box, with the bits wrapped in little plastic bags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/viscount.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;An Aires Viscount rangefinder camera. The base is silvery, the body black leatheret and the top is silvery.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after having a small meltdown when my husband pulled this out of the cupboard I actually looked at the camera. And held it. This thing is massive. With no case, no attachments, no film, it weighs a cool 813g. With my 50mm lens on, my modern Nikon weighs 650g. But this is built like a tank. Everything has a very satisfying &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; to it. It’s fully mechanical, and the rangefinder focusing still works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/cameras/attachments.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Viscount camera with selenium light meter and telephoto lens attachements.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera doesn’t have a built-in light meter of any kind. Aparently selenium light meters decay over time with exposure to light, so this might be a good thing. The camera came with two meters, both of which seem to work. The Aires one that attaches to the camera hotshoe is missing its front cover so doesn’t work in very bright light any more. The handheld light meter is a different brand, but works just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The telephoto lens attachement is very heavy and kind of crazy. It’s got quite a curve to it, I wonder how much that distorts the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grandpa would have bought this camera when he visited Japan in the early sixties. He used it I think until the late 80s. My mum can remember him using it on holidays, but Grandpa must not have used it much once the children left home as Dad doesn’t remember it. There’s certainly plenty of evidence, in film negatives and slides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like both of these cameras. You might think my gushing over the vintage chic means I like the Aires more, but they are actually both great cameras for different audiences. I think it’s great that both of them exist. The Kodak’s role has been subsumed by smartphones, and even the Aires has been to some extent. Some day I’d like to get some film and try them. Although Kodak has stopped making 110 film, &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.lomography.com/en/films/110-film?country=au&quot;&gt;Lomography&lt;/a&gt; makes it and a couple of places in Australia will still process it. Of course 35mm film is still available, although the price of film and development for even basic 35mm photography is a bit high. I probably won’t be using either any time soon, as my Fujifilm Instax camera is cheaper to use per shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might evict the Aires from the bag and put my Nikon in it. Seems a waste to keep such a lovely bag in the cupboard.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2018/06/12/two-cameras.html&quot;&gt;Two Cameras&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on June 12, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crippled by Design]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2018/04/23/crippled-by-design.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2018/04/23/crippled-by-design</id>
  <published>2018-04-23T00:00:00+10:00</published>
  <updated>2018-04-23T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/drawing2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of a woman curled up in bed drawing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two and a half years I’ve been gathering my thoughts about the iPad Pro. Through two major iOS versions, and even a refresh of the product line. This review has missed the news cycles by about 30 months minus 24 hours, but I think it’s now time to look back a little bit at the iPad Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-short-history-of-my-relationship-with-ipad&quot;&gt;A Short History of My Relationship with iPad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought the very &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPad_(1st_generation)&quot;&gt;first iPad&lt;/a&gt; shortly after launch. I was a student, it was far too much money to spend. I got the 3G model which was daft, 3G coverage at my uni was terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to take notes for uni on it, which I did with a fat stylus that looked like a giant rubber-tipped crayon. I thought it was glorious, but really it was very slow and for the most part I switched back to typing my lecture notes on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never buy a first-gen Apple product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my first Real Job out of Uni, one of the various projects I was put on was to port an app to iPad. There was an Android tablet app, and a desktop app, but iPad was The New Hotness and so they bought me an iPad 2 to develop with and left me to do it mostly by myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second-generation iPad was a vast improvement, but what I learnt about most was the limitations of the platform. As a user, I’d been frustrated by bugs; as a developer I realised how easy it was to make a mistake, and how many bugs were actually part of the OS. As a user I’d been annoyed by the app-islands, as a dev these islands pretty heavily limited how useful the product could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that for the most part the problems with the iPad were Apple’s to fix. The hardware was slow, the devices were heavy, the screens were iffy, the keyboards were dodgy, the styluses were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.engadget.com/2010/02/11/south-korean-iphone-users-turn-to-sausages-as-a-cold-weather-me/&quot;&gt;sausages&lt;/a&gt;, the OS was buggy, the app-centric model was very limiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I held onto the iPad 2 until I got a free&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; iPad Air. The iPad Air fixed the weight and screen issues, and was a big step forward on speed as well. With iOS 9 we finally got something &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2015/06/12/ios-9-ipad-multitasking-feature/&quot;&gt;not entirely unlike multitasking&lt;/a&gt;. I could see that Apple was moving in the right direction. I continued to use rubber-tipped styluses for iPad art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the iPad Pro was first announced I was dumbstruck. A stylus? When Steve Jobs had famously mocked styluses during the &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2015/09/10/technology/apple-pencil-steve-jobs-stylus/index.html&quot;&gt;original iPhone announcement&lt;/a&gt;? But not just any stylus—Apple didn’t want to be in the game if they couldn’t rival &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wacom_(company)&quot;&gt;Wacom&lt;/a&gt;. And Apple were making a keyboard case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then the prices were announced, and ouch. The 32GB model was priced &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smh.com.au/technology/apples-ipad-pro-available-this-week-in-australia—but-itll-cost-you-20151110-gkuv8v.html&quot;&gt;just under an 11-inch MacBook Air&lt;/a&gt;, add the Apple Pencil and they were the same. Add a keyboard or more storage and the iPad was more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The price meant the iPad Pro was presenting me with a completely new question. Could an iPad be my main home computer? Not my work computer of course, I wasn’t going to try compiling Ada on an iPad&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Not the only computer in my home either, eTax wasn’t yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ato.gov.au/Individuals/Lodging-your-tax-return/In-detail/MyTax-replaces-e-tax/&quot;&gt;myTax&lt;/a&gt;, and I’d need some way to backup my photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also looking at the Surface Pro. The Surface Pro was the enemy I knew, Windows&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. On paper it ticked all the boxes. It actually ticked more boxes than the iPad Pro because I knew the software was already there. Picking the iPad Pro, I was gambling that the software on iPad would catch up to the capabilities of the Surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It kind of has. I’m still not &lt;em&gt;certain&lt;/em&gt; I made the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/ipad1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of the iPad 1 with a stylus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ergonomics&quot;&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 12.9 inch iPad Pro is a curious in-between size. It’s too big to really hold in one hand comfortably. It weighs just over 700g on its own, and around 850g with a Smart Cover. That’s just shy of a MacBook which is 900g. The smaller Pro comes in under 500g. You can kind of hold the large iPad Pro in one hand and use it with the other hand, like a large picture book. This works better in landscape than in portrait, in portrait it’s a bit top-heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the only time I use the iPad Pro in portrait is when an app (or the system) forces me to, otherwise I live in landscape. The landscape on-screen keyboard is almost the size of a real keyboard so I can do a passable job of touch-typing on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But still, it’s too heavy to hold up and use in landscape. Even with two hands, using the slightly bizarre split thumb keyboard, it’s too heavy and too big. My arms get tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means you’re going to want the iPad Pro supported on something. Your lap is the obvious choice. I’m often curled up on the couch with the iPad flat against my thighs, or wedged between me and the back of the couch in some way. This isn’t comfortable for a long time, but I’m a wriggler so it kind of works for me if I’m mostly not typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way to use it would be to with some kind of table or desk. I have &lt;em&gt;issues&lt;/em&gt; with desks, so while some people might be able to use a laptop on a table at a cafe, I would find that at first uncomfortable and after a while, painful. At work I have a carefully positioned external monitor that my laptop plugs into. My chair, keyboard, and monitor are positioned &lt;em&gt;just so&lt;/em&gt;. This is basically impossible to do with the iPad Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I type this post, I’m doing my best attempt at an ergonomic setup. I have the iPad Pro on a Logitech stand that holds it at 15º or so from vertical. That is on top of a toy box which is about 30 cm tall. Then on the desk I have the matching Logitech keyboard. It’s a bit precarious, but there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://sixcolors.com/post/2018/04/writing-on-my-ipad-at-home/&quot;&gt;better solutions&lt;/a&gt; that are less cobbled-together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large iPad Pro isn’t really any easier than a MacBook to fit into a bag, and you have to fit in a separate keyboard with the iPad. There’s no way to have a separate display &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; be plugged into power with the iPad. With the single USB-C port of the MacBook you can have power and display with the (stupidly expensive) USB-C to HDMI adapter or a USB-C monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ports-portrait-landscape&quot;&gt;Ports, Portrait, Landscape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of ports, the iPad Pro actually has &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than the MacBook. Both have a headphone jack. The MacBook has a single USB-C port for charging, connecting peripherals, or an extra display. The iPad has a lightning port for the same, although with a smaller range of adapters and capabilities. The iPad Pro has one more port, which I pretty much always forget about because only two devices use it. The Smart Connector can be used to attach either the Apple keyboard or the Logitech one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory the USB-C port on the MacBook could let you live the USB dream of a massive mess of hubs connecting countless devices, but the reality is that there’s not a lot of high-quality adapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no complaints about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MK0W2AM/A/lightning-to-usb-3-camera-adapter&quot;&gt;Lightning to USB 3 Camera adapter&lt;/a&gt;.
It can’t be used to connect external file storage, but using it for USB MIDI or with a USB Audio interface works fine, and the extra power means I don’t worry about the dreaded “This device draws too much power” message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem with ports on the iPad Pro is their location, one each on three sides. Two of those are in the middle of their side, and one is up in the corner. Look at a laptop, and you’ll find the ports on either side towards the back, together. Some old ones will have ports on the back under the hinge. But the iPad Pro isn’t used in just one orientation the way a laptop is. With the ports spread around there’s always one that’s in an inconvenient spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure Jony Ive loves the symmetry of having the Lightning port in the middle under the home button. I don’t. Put it on the corner. Oh, and the Smart Connector is a neat idea for an extra port-without-a-hole, but Apple needs to do more with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most obvious example of Apple not thinking about the iPad is the Music Memos app. It’s just a blown up version of the iPhone app. On the iPad Mini that’s excusable, on the 12.9 inch iPad that’s crazy. It has the same layout in landscape as portrait, and hasn’t been updated to support the large iPad size. It has four button on the whole screen, just adding more empty space to take up the same UI as the app has on an iPhone SE on the whole 12.9 inch iPad Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some third-party apps &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; support portrait orientation, which generally means I delete them quickly. And for some reason I can’t fathom, after a system update the iPad requires you to type your passcode in portrait (must be fun if you’ve got a keyboard case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “legacy” iPhone-on-an-iPad view, which is still around, respects the device orientation as well. So if the iPhone app doesn’t offer a landscape view you’re stuck on iPad. And yes, this is still a thing you have to do, because many apps still do not support iPad at all. Let alone iPad Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/drawing1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of a woman sitting on a couch holding an iPad and drawing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;with-the-pencil&quot;&gt;With the Pencil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite way to use the iPad is with the Apple Pencil, they’re such a great pair. But when you’re not using them, when you’re carrying them together or charging the pencil, it’s daft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To charge the pencil, you need to connect it to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/how-charge-your-apple-pencil&quot;&gt;some kind of lightning port&lt;/a&gt;. They’re expecting you to plug it into the iPad, but it looks silly and takes up a huge amount of space. It makes it hard to charge while sitting on the couch. I can only imagine how annoying it would be on an aeroplane tray table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not even hard to fix the problem, just make the lightning end able to twist so the port is on the side. Then it would sit nicely along the side of the iPad. Charging with the iPad is a good idea; the iPad has a huge battery and only one power port. The pencil also comes with the teeny-tiny lightning cable adapter (female-to-female) which is very easy to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of losing things, there’s no easy way to carry the pencil and iPad together without a third-party case. The new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MQ0Q2FE/A/leather-sleeve-for-129%E2%80%91inch-ipad-pro-saddle-brown&quot;&gt;leather sleeve cases&lt;/a&gt; do have a slot for the pencil, but the Smart Cover has nothing. You can get the pencil to stick a bit to the magnets on the front of the iPad, kind of like the old iMac &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2009/11/04/apples-new-remote-is-a-riddle-wrapped-in-a-mystery-inside-an-enigma/&quot;&gt;remote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cover-stand&quot;&gt;Cover, Stand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve used any of the other sizes of iPad, you’re probably familiar with the Smart Cover (and the many similar designs by other manufacturers). The Smart Cover has had a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-au/HT204158&quot;&gt;very similar&lt;/a&gt; incarnations; the original had four panels and a metal hinge, these days they have three and a fabric hinge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On every other size iPad I consider the Smart Cover to be a must-have accessory. But the cover for the largest iPad really doesn’t work well. It seems that while the Smart Cover scales down from the original size nicely to the iPad Mini, on the iPad Pro it doesn’t scale up well. The cover itself is relatively heavy, which means it doesn’t stick as well to the magnets that keep it closed. There is a lot more twist in it, which means it doesn’t stay in the correct shape quite as well. Closed, folded behind, or folded up as a stand, it has a tendency to collapse. The weight of the iPad Pro also means that it has a disturbing tendency to tip backwards. Thankfully my iPad hasn’t fallen much further than my lap to the couch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason the Smart Cover only comes in two “colours”, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MQ0G2FE/A/smart-cover-for-129‑inch-ipad-pro-charcoal-grey&quot;&gt;black and white&lt;/a&gt;. I have the white one, and yes it was discoloured almost immediately. They did eventually add the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MPV22FE/A/leather-smart-cover-for-129‑inch-ipad-pro-midnight-blue&quot;&gt;leather Smart Cover&lt;/a&gt; in navy blue, brown, and black. Compare that to the 10.9 inch iPad Pro which has &lt;em&gt;thirteen&lt;/em&gt; colours in the regular Smart Cover and eight in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MPUA2FE/A/leather-smart-cover-for-105‑inch-ipad-pro-midnight-blue&quot;&gt;leather&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/typing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of an iPad on top of a cardboard box with a keyboard in front of it, setup like an old desktop PC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keyboard&quot;&gt;Keyboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m typing this review right now on a bluetooth keyboard connected to my iPad Pro. It’s a fairly mediocre Logitech keyboard, with a few function keys (volume, home, search), and inexplicably no escape key&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I picked it up second-hand for $6. It also has a case which turns into an iPad stand. A couple of months ago the keyboard stopped working, and I thought I’d have to replace it. Thankfully it came back to life because the alternatives aren’t great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Apple shows in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=sQB2NjhJHvY&quot;&gt;cute ad&lt;/a&gt; is their own Smart Keyboard. Coming in at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/smart-keyboard/&quot;&gt;$245&lt;/a&gt; that better be one hell of a keyboard. The Wirecutter puts it as their &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewirecutter.com/reviews/best-ipad-pro-keyboard-cases/&quot;&gt;top recommendation&lt;/a&gt; but the many reports of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/shop/reviews/MJYR2LL/A/smart-keyboard-for-129-inch-ipad-pro-us-english&quot;&gt;connectivity issues&lt;/a&gt; in iOS 11 are worrying. A keyboard needs to be rock solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, most of the problems you’re going to have with a keyboard and the iPad you’re going to have with any keyboard, and any iPad.  Because it’s really painfully obvious that Apple isn’t testing iOS with a keyboard, and most third-party software developers aren’t either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re an old-school Mac user, you’re probably used to doing things like command-click or ctrl-click. Even if you’re not you might be used to holding down shift and clicking to select text or documents. There’s no keyboard and touch combined interaction with the iPad. This makes perfect sense in a world where you’re using an on-screen keyboard, but when I have a proper keyboard connected, it feels quite jarring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also realised how much I rely on keyboard navigation on a laptop. There’s a lot of places in iOS where you can get “stuck” when trying to tab through fields or controls and the only way out is to tap. (This might be better if my keyboard had an escape key.) There are various problems with software which is attempting to respect an on-screen keyboard that isn’t there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a hardware keyboard, there’s no way to switch focus between apps that are open in multi-tasking. There’s no way to add an app to split view, get rid of split view, or show an app in slide-over. If you have an app in slide-over and you command-tab to a different app and back, the slide-over will be gone. If I have a keyboard connected, I often just pretend that split view and slide-over aren’t there and use every app in full screen mode. I can command-tab fast enough that this is only mildly irritating rather than infuriating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command-tab based switcher, for some reason, is not the same as the switcher you get when you double-tap home or swipe the dock up. So when switching between apps with a keyboard there’s no way to tell which are split and which not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;windowing-without-windows&quot;&gt;Windowing Without Windows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When iOS 9 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/ipad-multitasking&quot;&gt;introduced multitasking&lt;/a&gt; on iPad I was thrilled (even though I didn’t get to use it for a while because I had an older iPad). Once I was using it on the iPad Pro I quickly came to depend on split screen, and I got annoyed by it every time I used it. The picker for the second app was very bad, as it only had one mode: most recently used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried very hard not to get excited about the iOS 11 improvements to multitasking. I didn’t want to be disappointed again. But I was. Instead of having a giant list of apps sorted by most recent, you now get to pick from the apps in your dock and a few “suggestions”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. You can actually use &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; two apps in split view, although Apple’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-au/HT207582&quot;&gt;knowledge base article&lt;/a&gt; makes no mention of it. As Serenity Caldwell &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/how-use-slide-over-and-split-view-ipad-ios-11#add&quot;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt;, from the home screen tap-and-drag one app with one finger, and then while dragging, tap the other app with a different finger. It does work if the apps are on different home screens or in folders, but it is more annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still only split with each app once. So if you want to split your text editor with Safari and Mail with Safari? Tough luck, you’ll have to re-split them each time you switch. To date, Safari is the only Apple app you can split inside itself, and that only works when Safari has the screen to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elephant in the split-view room is that many apps still do not support split view. I have 143 apps on my iPad, only five of those are games. Of the 143 apps, only 74 support split view. The list that don’t support split view includes Apple apps like GarageBand and iMovie, as well as major third-party apps like Gmail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even still have a very few apps I need on my iPad that run in the phone-on-an-iPad view. The app for my little Fuji printer, the app to control my digital piano, and an app I use to speed up video because iMovie can’t go faster than double speed. If Apple stopped supporting this view in some ways it would be good—it’s a terrible user experience—but it would be really annoying to have to use my phone for those things instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-party-apps&quot;&gt;First-Party Apps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/apps.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The app icons for iMovie, GarageBand, Photos and Files&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;imovie&quot;&gt;iMovie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/my-97-ipad-2018-review-drawn-written-edited-and-produced-ipad&quot;&gt;review of the 2018 iPad and Apple Pencil&lt;/a&gt;, one of Serenity Caldwell’s complaints was iMovie. In order to create time-lapses of her screen recordings, she had to use a third party app which could speed them up as much as 8 times. If she wanted faster, she had to export and re-import to apply more speed. Why couldn’t she do this in iMovie? You &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; speed up clips in iMovie on iPad, but only up to double speed. On the Mac, you can adjust the speed however you like, just type in a multiplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, but &lt;em&gt;on the Mac&lt;/em&gt; seems to be a thing I say every time I try and use iMovie on iPad. It’s not just a little bit cut down, it’s incredibly crippled. Some things like chromakey are missing entirely. Other things like transition length and clip speed only give you a few presets rather than on the Mac where you can set any value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On iPad it’s missing lots of features, which I could forgive perhaps if there was a Final Cut Pro for iPad. But there isn’t. The best video editor for iPad is iMovie, and that is really sad. When I was in high school, one of the reasons people bought a Mac at all was &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; for iMovie. On iPad, iMovie feels like a trial version, not a full app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, there’s no easy way to work on the same video on iOS and on Mac. With GarageBand you can store your work in iCloud easily, but iMovie can’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;garageband&quot;&gt;GarageBand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After quite a lot of neglect, GarageBand just received a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2018/03/27/apple-updates-clips-and-garageband-education/&quot;&gt;small update&lt;/a&gt;. But the two major issues with GarageBand are still haunting me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first should be trivial to fix. The maximum project length needs to be extended. It’s currently 25 minutes, which is fine for a pop song but not enough for a video score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is much harder. There’s a pretty powerful inter-app audio system in iOS that allows you to route audio and MIDI between various apps. So in theory I can set up &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.korg.com/us/products/software/korg_im1_for_ipad/&quot;&gt;Korg iM1&lt;/a&gt; to take my piano’s MIDI out, and then take the sound out of iM1 and put that into GarageBand and record it. And &lt;em&gt;in theory&lt;/em&gt; I could first route that audio through another app to apply effects, or route the MIDI through two apps and mix the sound later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that inter-app audio works for simple setups, but not for complex ones. That’s largely because it’s impossible to see what is actually going on. There needs to be some way in GarageBand to view the full routing setup for audio and MIDI and &lt;em&gt;edit&lt;/em&gt; that setup. It should work without having to go out to each app and change its settings, or in some cases force-quit apps to get them to “release” the inter-app audio connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally on my wish list is the ability to record multiple audio sources. I realise that’s a bit of a pipe dream, since you’d need the camera connection kit and a powered USB hub in order to connect multiple audio devices, but it would be super sweet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photos&quot;&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my complaints about Apple’s Photos app apply across iPhone and iPad. For example, iCloud photos performs poorly with large photo libraries on both devices. Both have lots of apps that use the photo picker but haven’t been updated to expect iCloud photo library and so can’t do anything with photos that haven’t been downloaded. Not even on Mac is there any way to really know what iCloud photo library is doing, and if it gets stuck in some way you only have one button: turn off iCloud photo library. Which gives you scary warnings about deleting all your photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On iPad, with the fast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MJYT2AM/A/lightning-to-sd-card-camera-reader&quot;&gt;SD card reader&lt;/a&gt;, I can import JPEGs at a good speed, and RAWs at an acceptable speed&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But the part of Photos that is uniquely terrible on iPad is the photo selection view. Loading the thumbnails is only marginally faster than just downloading them all and culling them later. The previews are really small, so while you’ll have an okay idea of composition and exposure (things that can sometimes be rescued in edit) you can’t really tell if the photo is in focus. And there’s no way to edit a photo to change the focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be a marked improvement if it was possible to use the camera connection kit to import photos into &lt;em&gt;anywhere&lt;/em&gt; else. For most people I think Lightroom mobile would be the obvious candidate, but it would also be useful to save them to Files. Then they could be added to your cloud storage of choice: iCloud drive, Dropbox, Google or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;files-vs-finder&quot;&gt;Files vs Finder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Files is my great hope for the iPad as an environment for getting work done. When Apple first announced Files, I wasn’t sure exactly what the point was. But as more apps and syncing services have started supporting Files, I’ve realised that Files is Finder for the iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that seems obvious, but Files is actually a pretty big change for iOS. A central shared space for all your files in various cloud services is incredibly useful, because it can be accessed by a variety of apps. I can have folders based on projects, with different media types in them and open them with different apps. Welcome to Classic Mac OS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately in some ways Files is still an exciting &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; rather than an exciting &lt;em&gt;reality&lt;/em&gt;. At the moment, file management in Files is cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renaming files requires a long press to get a popup menu, and then you get a modal dialogue to enter the name. Inline editing with a single touch on the file name would be a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to move files around is also not easy. It’s a shame, because this should be the place where iOS 11’s drag-and-drop features shine. If Files could be split with itself, it would be easy to organise files. Seems so simple!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be good to have another feature of Finder, tabs. That way a user could have a series of different locations open to easily jump between them. Or even &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt;. Crazy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Files also has some problematic bugs. Every other day it seems it will just stop showing any files or changing folders, and the only way to get it back is to restart the device. If there was a bug like that in Finder, it would be considered a major system issue. With the growing importance of Files to the iOS system, I think Apple needs to really clean up their bug backlog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/restart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An illustration of the &amp;quot;Slide to power off&amp;quot; screen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting-in-the-dark&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting in the Dark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation I’m having with Files isn’t unique to that app. All over iOS I have issues, and it’s very hard, or impossible, to work out what is wrong and do anything about it. The only technique is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Force quit and reopen the app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restart the device&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinstall the app (if possible) (which will delete your data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For non-Apple apps, at this point all you can do is contact the developer and hope they’re able to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Apple apps or iOS bugs you get a few more steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wipe the device and reinstall iOS, all your apps and all your data, from a backup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wipe the device and reinstall iOS and your apps and data from scratch, you will probably lose data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have an Apple Store nearby, and they have any Genius Bar appointments available, go in and try and get them to fix it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What iOS needs is some way for advanced users to get access to more information. You can get access to a limited amount of extra information by connecting the iPad to a Mac, but an iPad that’s only an accessory to a Mac doesn’t have a bright future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/flowchart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A flowchart showing a loop that rolls a dice ten times&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workflow-is-not-magic&quot;&gt;Workflow is Not Magic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://workflow.is&quot;&gt;Workflow&lt;/a&gt; is very cool, and very clever. Within the sandbox of iOS, the developers have built up an app that almost has the power of &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-au/guide/automator/welcome/mac&quot;&gt;Automator&lt;/a&gt;. It has also integrated with various social network services, making content sharing a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is even more exciting about Workflow is that Apple has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2017/3/22/15030462/apple-acquires-workflow-iphone-utility&quot;&gt;bought it&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.workflow.is/whatsnew&quot;&gt;hasn’t abandoned it&lt;/a&gt;. I’m optimistic that Workflow will get more integrations with more services and apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However cool Workflow is, like Automator, there’s always a point where it just can’t do enough. As a developer, I’m used to being able to fill this gap with things I make myself; mostly scripts but sometimes I put in the effort to make them into something worth at least throwing up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one half-solution to this on iOS at the moment, &lt;a href=&quot;http://omz-software.com/pythonista/&quot;&gt;Pythonista&lt;/a&gt;. But what iOS really needs isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/swift/playgrounds/&quot;&gt;Playgrounds&lt;/a&gt; or Pythonista, it needs &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/&quot;&gt;Xcode&lt;/a&gt;. When you can develop apps for iOS on iOS, the circle will be complete and the iPad and iPhone will truly be untethered from the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/floppy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An illustration of a floppy disk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;file--save-or-how-i-learned-to-give-up-and-embrace-terrible-ports&quot;&gt;File &amp;gt; Save or How I Learned to Give Up and Embrace Terrible Ports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed a small trend in iOS development. An increasing number of apps I’m using are throwing away the Human Interface Guidelines. They’re making small buttons, with less than &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/ios/human-interface-guidelines/visual-design/adaptivity-and-layout/&quot;&gt;44x44pt as a minimum tap target size&lt;/a&gt;. They’re implementing menus with titles like &lt;em&gt;File&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Edit&lt;/em&gt;. They have save buttons. The save buttons have &lt;em&gt;floppy disk icons&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically these apps are porting their Windows or Mac app to iOS with few if any changes. In some ways, I’m horrified. Apple hasn’t sold a Mac with a floppy drive since 2000; I’m sure many students getting iPads for school or home have never even seen a floppy. On the other hand, the density of information and controls is refreshing. It’s nice to see a UI which isn’t a giant bold heading floating in a white landscape like a modernist artwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m worried that this trend shows that large companies aren’t seeing the value in substantially rethinking their apps when porting them for iOS. I’m also worried that Apple will dismiss this out-of-hand as bad design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the iPad to move forward, the density of information in “Pro” apps must increase, or users will become frustrated as common tasks require more steps. So far I haven’t seen Apple particularly interested in addressing density. The worst example is Music Memos, but even Pages and Numbers have issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Apple doesn’t take the iPad Pro seriously, who will?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/ipad-pro/future.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A future iPad with no home button, with a Smart Cover folded behind as a stand. Shows three apps split on screen with lots of buttons and options&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hope&quot;&gt;Hope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design and development are an iterative process. An entire computing platform wasn’t released with the original iPhone in 2007; over the past eleven years Apple has been expanding, rewriting, rethinking and learning on the job. As a developer myself I know my greatest struggle is often with my past self who made mistakes and choices that I now regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Apple keep up the pressure on themselves to improve and outdo their own work, then I’m confident that the iPad Pro does have a bright future as the next generation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nMsZ-GSKORM&quot;&gt;personal computer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Free as in I was buying something else much more expensive, I’m sure it was basically included in the price. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, that would only be possible if you were just using the iPad to ssh through to a server. The closest you get to a real compiler on iPad at the moment is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/swift/playgrounds/&quot;&gt;Swift Playgrounds&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If they’ve fixed the bug where Windows 10 reboots to install updates while you have an open document with unsaved changes and you are actively using it, let me know. But that bug basically makes a computer &lt;em&gt;unusable&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve since found out that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fn + home&lt;/code&gt; is escape, but it’s not at all obvious. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This seems to be a mashup based on connected devices (like headphones) and recently used. Perhaps if the logic behind what it showed was more clear it would be more useful. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to be using the USB version of the camera connection, it’s slow, and for some reason mine won’t delete anything off my SD cards. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2018/04/23/crippled-by-design.html&quot;&gt;Crippled by Design&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on April 23, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[State of the Art 2018]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2018/03/12/state-of-the-art-2018.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2018/03/12/state-of-the-art-2018</id>
  <published>2018-03-12T02:00:00+11:00</published>
  <updated>2018-03-12T02:00:00+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/clip-studio-ipad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clip Studio on iPad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;changes&quot;&gt;Changes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first looked at digital painting in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/28/drawing-roundup.html&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt; (where I was largely disappointed). In &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/02/09/state-of-the-art-ipad.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt; I’d settled on Procreate on the iPad Pro 12.9” with the Apple Pencil. Since that review I’ve spent a lot more time painting—both on the iPad and with acrylics—and developers have spent time improving the tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware-wise, not a lot has changed; although Apple has released a new large and regular-sized iPad Pro, I haven’t been tempted to update yet. There hasn’t been a new Apple Pencil. I’m still hopeful that Apple will find a way to make the pencil work without a battery, or at least find a way to charge it where it doesn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.macrumors.com/attachments/image-jpeg.580195/&quot;&gt;look absurd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clip-studio-on-ipad&quot;&gt;Clip Studio on iPad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.celsys.co.jp/en/topic/20171108&quot;&gt;November 2017&lt;/a&gt; CELSYS released &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/clip-studio-paint-ex-for-manga/id1262985592?mt=8&quot;&gt;Clip Studio Paint EX&lt;/a&gt; (what a mouthful), which is basically the Windows tablet-optimised version of Clip Studio/Manga Studio&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I only found out much later, but I jumped right in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app has me completely divided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love most about Clip Studio is the colour blending and brushes, and the iPad app has nailed this. It feels exactly like the Windows or Mac version. The watercolour brushes are fluid and soft, the oils are buttery, the pencil is responsive, the pressure sensitivity is bang on. I imported a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://kayleefuzzyhat.deviantart.com/art/358-Copic-Color-Set-for-Clip-Studio-Paint-575059284&quot;&gt;Copic colours&lt;/a&gt; and was off; it was how I’d always wanted my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asus.com/Tablets/ASUS_VivoTab_Note_8_M80TA/&quot;&gt;Asus Vivo Note 8&lt;/a&gt; to be (which is to say: not running Windows, much larger, not dead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside of this app is that it feels &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; like the desktop version. There’s a ‘File’ menu and a save button with a &lt;em&gt;floppy disk icon&lt;/em&gt;! This app would be impossible to use without the Apple Pencil, because all the buttons are tiny. The app does support the iPad split view properly, but it has no integration with Files so any documents have to be manually exported using what looks like a hack on the save dialogue. Being somewhat tablet optimised, the app does support pinch-to-zoom and pinch-to-rotate, which really is a must have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having spent a lot of time with &lt;a href=&quot;https://procreate.art&quot;&gt;Procreate&lt;/a&gt;, Clip Studio on iPad looks incredibly old-fashioned and feels out-of-place. However, having all the buttons just &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; on the screen with no hidden gestures or swipe-to-reveal has reminded me that desktop apps have something to offer. Particularly on the (giant) iPad Pro 12.9”, you can actually fit in a lot of buttons. You don’t need to hide things behind other things, or use a triple-three-finger-tap. One of the things I strongly dislike about Procreate is how many common tasks (alpha lock, layer opacity, paste) are hidden behind gestures that I keep forgetting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m just old, but for me the wonder of the &lt;em&gt;graphical&lt;/em&gt; user interface is that everything is just there. Gestures feel like being thrown to a terminal for an unfamiliar OS. How do I copy again? Was it select and middle-click or double-tap with two fingers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clip Studio EX has a six-month free trial, which is quite generous. But after that it’s AU$12 a month. Ouch. I already own the desktop version of Clip Studio, and I paid around USD$60/AUD$80 for a perpetual licence. The iPad version will cost that much after seven months. I completely understand why developers are moving to a subscription model, as it’s almost impossible to charge enough up-front and maintain enough momentum for growth to have sustainable income. In addition, the App Store continues to have no way to offer upgrade pricing, which was a key component of the pre-App Store pricing world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the moment, I’ve set a six-month reminder for when my free trial ends, and I’ll see then how much I value having Clip Studio on iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changes-in-ios-11&quot;&gt;Changes in iOS 11&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When iOS 11 was announced I was stoked. But after I patiently waited through the beta period&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I was actually disappointed. In iOS 10 I’d removed a bunch of apps from my iPad, because the list in the slide-over pane was too long. But now you have to do this crazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultofmac.com/490710/slide-over-split-view-ios-11/&quot;&gt;tap-hold-drag dance&lt;/a&gt; to get two apps open side-by-side. And you can only have each app once, so if you want to see two windows of Safari next to different apps, tough luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am loving the new Files app (although not the name, can Apple please hire someone who can name things). It makes it a lot easier to deal with my mess of documents across iCloud, Dropbox and Google Drive. It could do with having a split view, that would make moving files around a lot easier. I’ve also noticed how much I navigate Finder on the Mac with my keyboard, which doesn’t work at all with Files. I hope they expand the keyboard support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also hopeful that Apple’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2018/01/30/apple-to-focus-on-ios-performance-quality-issues-axios/&quot;&gt;rumoured renewed focus on quality&lt;/a&gt; will mean that iOS 12 delivers fixes for some of the continuing infuriating bugs I see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the iPad Pro is definitely improving, it has a long way to go, so I’m still keeping an eye out to see what the alternatives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;microsoft&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft (&lt;a href=&quot;https://daringfireball.net/linked/2011/09/29/finally&quot;&gt;finally!&lt;/a&gt;) updated the Surface Pro 4 to the “New” Surface Pro&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The biggest change here appears to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slashgear.com/surface-pro-4-vs-surface-pro-is-it-worth-the-upgrade-25486416/&quot;&gt;battery life and the i5 not having a fan&lt;/a&gt;. Both nice to have, but Microsoft still doesn’t offer enough options. To increase the storage you have to go up a CPU, and the same for the RAM. It’s a shame, because I think a Surface Pro with an i5, 512GB or even 1TB of storage, and 8GB of RAM would be pretty sweet. The m3 version also only has 4GB of RAM and 64GB of storage, which is just way too low for both. Intel’s m3 processor is actually pretty sweet, offering a good compromise for an ultra-portable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it still runs Windows. Which is a pity, as my last experience of Windows 10 involved it shutting down to install updates while I was actively working on an open document with unsaved changes. I know other people complain about it doing that overnight, and to be honest I think that’s also pretty annoying. But updating while you’re using it makes it feel like it’s done a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_Screen_of_Death&quot;&gt;BSoD&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe I’ll try again when Windows 11 comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft continues to sell the Surface Pro without the keyboard or the pen, which adds about AU$400 to the price. Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wacom&quot;&gt;Wacom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old guard in digital art is Wacom. And indeed I still use a Wacom graphics tablet at work as a mouse replacement. Wacom’s entry-level no-screen graphics tablets have just seen an update that brings &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/circuitbreaker/2018/3/6/17085562/wacom-intuos-drawing-tablet&quot;&gt;bluetooth to the low end&lt;/a&gt; which is welcome given how many laptops these days are dropping ports or only have USB-C ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the complete opposite end, Wacom showed off its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/1/9/16871162/wacom-cintiq-32-inch-drawing-tablet-ces-2018&quot;&gt;32” Cintiq&lt;/a&gt; at CES, along with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/circuitbreaker/2018/2/27/17058484/wacom-cintiq-pro-24-engine-pc-module&quot;&gt;Cintiq Pro Engine&lt;/a&gt;, a plug-in PC for the 26” and 32” behemoths. At around US$3.5k each for the display and the PC these aren’t really &lt;em&gt;consumer&lt;/em&gt; electronics. But Cintiqs like these are what hobbyist digital artists drool over (and pros sweat over paying off).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle is Wacom’s own tablet PC, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wacom.com/en-au/products/pen-computers/wacom-mobilestudio-pro&quot;&gt;Mobile Studio Pro&lt;/a&gt; which comes in 13” and 16” models. In Australia the 13” Wacom is substantially more expensive than the Surface at the low end, but similar at the high end. The 16” model is AU$4.5k for the 512GB model, which is eye-watering. However, nobody else is offering a similar extra-large tablet option (even if it does weigh 2.2kg) and I applaud Wacom for continuing to try new options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wacom tablets that come with a PC of course run Windows 10, but all of them can be used as an extra display for a Mac as well. Unlike &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.windowscentral.com/why-no-usb-type-c-new-surface-pro&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;, Wacom is embracing USB-C with the Cintiq Pro and Mobile Studio Pro having USB-C ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;astropad-studio&quot;&gt;Astropad Studio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounding up the set of too many products ending in &lt;em&gt;Pro&lt;/em&gt;, is… oh wait. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://astropad.com/studio/&quot;&gt;Astropad Studio&lt;/a&gt;. Both the Standard and Studio versions of Astropad take your Mac’s screen and put it on your iPad, passing through the inputs. For Standard, this includes some stylus pressure sensitivity into some Mac apps. Studio is built specifically for the Apple Pencil, and is optimised to reduce lag for that one stylus. Reviews have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/ipad-pro-and-astropad-studio-i-may-never-need-wacom-tablet-again&quot;&gt;overwhelmingly positive&lt;/a&gt;, but my experience is that it’s only &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lag between the iPad and the Mac means the iPad software has to show you a little preview line so you know where you’re going, letting the Mac app catch up. This is better than the alternative of the line lagging behind the pencil, but it’s not as good as native iPad software which can have so little lag it feels like a real pencil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem is that the Mac and the iPad’s screens aren’t the same size. They’re not even the same aspect ratio. So you can choose between squishing your Mac screen onto your iPad, or cutting a section out and viewing that. Squishing means that everything is tiny, even on the 12.9” iPad. Cutting means there’s invariably some tool or window just out of reach and you have to go to your trackpad to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are basic limitations of third-party software attempting to bridge this gap. If there was a way to reboot the iPad into a display mode for the Mac, both of these problems would go away, but Apple seems highly unlikely to choose that path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;real-paint&quot;&gt;Real Paint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my knowledge there haven’t been any major advances in the technology of old-fashioned paint. But there has been a major advance in my understanding. Part way through this year I purchased some artist’s quality &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eckersleys.com.au/products/art/paints/acrylic-paints/liquitex-heavy-body-acrylic-paint&quot;&gt;heavy body&lt;/a&gt; acrylic paints. I’d always hated acrylics, the colours mixed in ways I didn’t like and the texture and final look were unappealing. I should have known from switching to artist’s quality watercolours that I could get a lot more enjoyment from acrylics than I had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality acrylic paints have filled the gap in my painting that occurred when I threw out my oils. Oil paints are beautiful, buttery, glossy. But they also need good ventilation and take forever to dry. Not practical in a small apartment. My new acrylics are not quite as good as oils, but finally I have opaque paints where I get what I expect when I mix colours. I can also add some gloss medium to make it a bit more creamy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The boxed retail version was called Manga Studio in the US, but I think people are finally coming around to calling it Clip Studio. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I write software, I know what can go wrong, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; install beta versions of iOS on my only iPad. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This was terrible when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPad_(3rd_generation)&quot;&gt;Apple did it&lt;/a&gt;, when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Nintendo_3DS&quot;&gt;Nintendo did it&lt;/a&gt;, I can’t fathom why Microsoft thought just sticking “New” on the front was a good idea. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2018/03/12/state-of-the-art-2018.html&quot;&gt;State of the Art 2018&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on March 12, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[State of the Art: iPad Pro + Pencil]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2017/02/09/state-of-the-art-ipad.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2017/02/09/state-of-the-art-ipad</id>
  <published>2017-02-09T00:00:00+11:00</published>
  <updated>2017-02-09T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-love-the-ipad-pro&quot;&gt;I love the iPad Pro&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iPad Pro first came out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPad_Pro&quot;&gt;late 2015&lt;/a&gt; and I snatched one up, along with the hard-to-find Apple Pencil. At the time I’d been dithering between a Surface Pro and the new iPad, but once I’d heard the latency tests for the Pencil come in I knew I wanted the iPad. Even though the software was very limited, and it’s not a fully-fledged PC, I wanted the best pen input for drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now 2017, so I’ve been using the iPad Pro and Pencil for over a year. In that time, there have been new art apps, and old ones have been updated and expanded to support the Apple Pencil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve divided the apps I’m looking at roughly into two groups. The first is apps designed for drawing or sketching, perhaps as a sketchbook or just a place to doodle, maybe with a dab of colour. The second group is apps designed for digital painting. I consider these quite different; although they could be used for sketches, they provide more advanced tools aimed at producing professional artworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m only looking at apps that support the large iPad Pro screen size in landscape. Apps which only have a regular-size iPad interface or only work in portrait have been excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I don’t know anymore which of these apps I paid for, were cheaper than now, or have otherwised changed their pricing model (paid up-front versus IAP). I have included the Australian pricing at the time of publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;drawing-and-sketching&quot;&gt;Drawing and Sketching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tayasui-sketches-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/3eQqM.i&quot;&gt;Tayasui Sketches →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free with AUD$9 IAP or AUD$9 upfront&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good range of tools with customisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layers and layer modes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lovely hatching fills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice pencil&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too much reliance on gestures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ink and paint tools too laggy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does not support iPad split screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paper-by-53-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/KfqkE.i&quot;&gt;Paper by 53 →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social features&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small range of tools, not much customisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ink and paint tools too laggy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watercolour behaviour erratic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doesn’t support split screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;autodesk-sketchbook-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/LzmR0.i&quot;&gt;Autodesk Sketchbook →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free with AUD$8 IAP, advanced tools also available as a AUD$8/month cross-platform subscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good interface, focus on the art&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layers and layer modes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excellent range of tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real paint emulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copic colours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quite responsive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DeviantArt integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supports iPad split screen&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lacks a good pencil tool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has some poor defaults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;painting&quot;&gt;Painting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;medibang-paint-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/eZy07.i&quot;&gt;Medibang Paint →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free with ads&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Manga Studio in Windows tablet mode, but without the vector or 3D tools&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excellent range of templates, including manga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stroke smoothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good digital and traditional emulation tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lots of tools for manga such as halftone and 8-bit layers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complicated interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has ads on main screen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does not support iPad split screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paintstorm-studio-lite-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/Dxszbb.i&quot;&gt;Paintstorm Studio (Lite) →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free for Lite, AUD$20 for full. Lite version only has JPEG export.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feels like Painter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good latency (without smoothing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stroke smoothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Excellent traditional emulation tools&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desktop style UI including File, Edit menus etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complicated interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strange zooming floating pallets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No native file format&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No gallery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;procreate-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/ATHvz.i&quot;&gt;Procreate →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AUD$10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excellent digital painting and drawing tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stroke smoothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layers and layer groups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supports iPad split screen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I love this app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What Next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art apps on iPad still have a long way to go. I want them to continue pushing the bounds, particularly reducing latency. It’s more noticeable in more complicated or smoothed tools, but it’s always there. Apple’s Notes app is often lauded for having the lowest latency, but I think without smoothing most of these apps’ pencil tools are just as fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also hope we get more tools for print, such as colour management and bleed markers. On the more digital end, I’d like to see more vector tools in digital painting apps. Now that Procreate has font smoothing, all it needs is text tools to become my one-stop art app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am worried about desktop apps porting to iPad. Initially, I was really excited by the idea of having the power of Manga Studio on iPad, but having seen how Medibang Paint and Paintstorm Lite have ported their interfaces, I’m now more tentative. I don’t want to see menu bars on an iPad, it’s just wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variety of sketching and drawing apps is great. I feel that there’s a good variety of styles, offering different social integrations. There’s definitely space to grow in the social drawing area, although I do hope that doesn’t become dominated with one app or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest and easiest gains on the iPad are actually Apple’s responsability. The split app view is super neat, and it would be even better if the app switcher and selector for the second app wasn’t a dumpster fire. I’ve had to uninstall apps I don’t use very often to clear space there, it’s stupid. Better inter-app communication is also needed to make it easier to sketch, ink, and paint in different apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apps on iPad continue to be very very cheap. If you’re used to shelling out $60 for a copy of Manga Studio or $30 a month for Photoshop, then the low pricing of iPad apps is amazing. The downside is that I do worry about their long-term viability at such low price points. I expect more apps, especially those coming from PC, will have subscription pricing models.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2017/02/09/state-of-the-art-ipad.html&quot;&gt;State of the Art: iPad Pro + Pencil&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on February 09, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPad Bibles - Study Time]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2016/10/08/bibles-for-ipad.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2016/10/08/bibles-for-ipad</id>
  <published>2016-10-08T00:00:00+11:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-08T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been over two years since I had a look at the iOS &lt;a href=&quot;2014-09-14-bible-roundup&quot;&gt;Bible landscape&lt;/a&gt;. Since an iPad is now my primary home computer, it seemed time to make a survey of the large-format Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are hundreds of Bible apps for iPhone, the market for iPad is much smaller. I feel that phone Bibles are replacing the pocket Bibles of old, a quick reference text and a resource you can take anywhere. On the iPad I think a Bible app has to offer something more. Some things I’m looking for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;View text across multiple columns (like an open book showing two pages)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-au/HT202070&quot;&gt;Split-screen multitasking&lt;/a&gt; between apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split screen within the app showing personal notes, other translations, study resources, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple translations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additional resources such as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;study notes (like in a study Bible)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;commentaries (single volume and multi-volume)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;maps&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;dictionaries&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;cross-referencing tools&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;interlinear Greek, Hebrew, Latin&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note, highlight, and bookmark management features (not limited to verse boundaries)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting all three iPad sizes (primarily the large iPad Pro)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at additional resources and translations, consider carefully what they are. Old commentaries are useful because they are (normally) free, and can provide important insight into the development of Christian theology. But some of these apps charge money for these old resources, and I worry that this might mislead some people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-fish&quot;&gt;Big Fish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big three Bible software companies, Tecarta, Faithlife (Logos), and HarperCollins (OliveTree), all provide a main app as well as extra applications with a particular in-app purchase included. In this case, I’ve looked at some of the variants and noted if they’re different, but I’m mainly focused on the primary app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/logos-tecarta.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tecarta and Logos&quot; /&gt;
Tecarta (left) and Logos (right) in split-screen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tecarta-inc&quot;&gt;Tecarta, Inc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main free versions of this app, the regular &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/I7ABt.i&quot;&gt;Tecarta app&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/AxFP4.i&quot;&gt;50th Anniversary NIV&lt;/a&gt; app. The Tecarta app contains only the KJV translation for free; even open translations such as the WEB cost money. The 50th Anniversary NIV comes with the 2011 NIV and a few reading plans, but you have to pay for the KJV. The apps are otherwise seemingly identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tecarta offers a standard list of translations, the only notables missing are the CEV, the NRSV, and the Jerusalem Bible. It is not clear if any translations contain the deuterocanonical books (the Apocrypha), but I suspect not. They also offer a few commentaries as in-app purchases, but in each case they are charging money for out-of-copyright works. There are, however, a selection of themed Study Bibles. Again, theses are priced equivalent to the paper versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app does support split-screen. It can be either the left or right app, and works great as both, adapting the interface to fit the space. The app also provides some minimal note-taking and highlighting tools, although I could only make these work on whole verses. While you can select less than a whole verse, there doesn’t appear to be any way to do anything with that selection, not even copy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;logos-faithlife-corporation&quot;&gt;Logos (Faithlife Corporation)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two apps here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/k-qdu.i&quot;&gt;Logos&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/6d89C.i&quot;&gt;Faithlife Study Bible&lt;/a&gt;. Both support the same resources and translations, although they have different defaults, and a very slightly different layout. For some reason the Faithlife version requires you to login, but this is skippable for Logos. The Faithlife app appears to only come with the LEB translation (produced by the same company). I am not sure what the Logos app comes with, as there are translations I can select in the books list which have a price tag in the shop, but it seems to come with the ESV, LEB and HCSB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are fewer translations here, and it feels like an odd selection but they are similarly priced to Olive Tree and Tecarta. There are a few study resources, but the selection is quite small, and once again they appear to be primarily out-of-copyright works for which they are charging money. However a look at the website shows thousands of books, so it would seem that they aren’t all available to purchase in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app also has an internal split view, and supports the iPad split view with other apps. It has very flexible highlighting and notes tools, but I have seen them be somewhat unresponsive which can be frustrating. I imagine on an older iPad this would be worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are excellent included note-taking and document (sermon) writing features&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, so I can see why this would be very popular with anyone regularly presenting lessons. It can also sync with the Proclaim church presentation software, so if your church uses that ecosystem that might be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;olive-tree-harpercollins-cristian-publishing&quot;&gt;Olive Tree (HarperCollins Cristian Publishing)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/olive-tree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Olive Tree&quot; /&gt;
Olive Tree showing split between Bible and notes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HarperCollins seem to have a never-ending list of apps, but they really only have two, &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/i_00t.i&quot;&gt;Olive Tree Bible+&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/DwmmE.i&quot;&gt;Bible Gateway&lt;/a&gt;, all the other apps are actually Olive Tree. The Bible Gateway app has two major flaws: it hasn’t been optimised for iPad Pro, and it contains ads. I’ve not seen any other Bible app with ads, and I’m not sure why the excellent Bible Gateway site thinks this is a good idea here. If you like the Bible Gateway site, just use that and skip the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olive Tree provides the most extensive collection of paid resources available as in-app purchases. There are maps, commentaries, study Bibles, dictionaries, cross-reference tools, and even just plain books. All of these are priced similar to the paper book price, but there is the convenience factor to consider, especially when some of these commentaries run to 60 volumes (and over a thousand dollars).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest disappointment about Olive Tree is that it still doesn’t support split view with other apps, only between books and resources inside Olive Tree. This internal split view is very good, it feels like a more modern paper study Bible. You can add highlights to any part of the text, no matter where the verse boundaries fall. There is also an extensive notes system which allows you to categorise and tag the information stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-publishers&quot;&gt;Other Publishers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;just1word&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/LxQDw.I&quot;&gt;Just1Word&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of Bibles by this publisher with different names but similar icons all showing a large number “1”. While these do support the larger screen sizes, they feel like scaled up versions of the iPhone applications, with skinny menus and huge paragraph widths. There is no way to split the text into columns or have side-by-side translations. These apps do not support split-screen with other apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ebible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/lwRyC.i&quot;&gt;eBible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app does not support the large iPad Pro, and does not support split screen within the app or with other apps. It has a standard range of translations and note taking features, but no additional resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youversion-bible-by-lifechurch&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/Agu3q.i&quot;&gt;Youversion Bible by Life.Church&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app on iPhone won my roundup. Unfortunately the iPad version doesn’t offer a lot more. It does have an internal split, which can show two different translations at the same time, but there are no extra resources and there is no book-style multi-column view. It has the same highlight and note features as the iPhone, and if you mainly use the iPhone version all that info syncs, which is handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bible-reader&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/BNr_R.i&quot;&gt;Bible Reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another favourite on iPhone fails to offer anything new on iPad. In addition, it doesn’t support the large iPad size. With no offline translations, this app is actually less useful than opening a Bible Gateway tab in Safari. At least that would support split screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;esv-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/zAjKv.i&quot;&gt;ESV Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app offers only a single translation, which isn’t surprising given the name. It doesn’t support the large iPad size, but it does support internal split with the three resources it provides or your own notes. It doesn’t support making notes or highlights on less than a whole verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;glo-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/xtvWz.i&quot;&gt;Glo Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Glo Bible has changed a lot in two years! This app is interesting in that rather than offering a lot of one-off in app purchases, it is mainly driven by a subscription. Extra translations are individual purchases and so are alternate themes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but maps and reference texts are available through subscription. This app only has a small selection of translations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glo supports splitting the screen with another app, but inside the app it splits top and bottom, not left and right, which is different. Not my preference, but I suppose if you split it with another app you get a kind of four-way split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accordance&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/sVIJy.i&quot;&gt;Accordance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Accordance app lets you split in either direction within the app, and supports iOS split screen with another app. However, it seems to have a few interface bugs: I found that sometimes the text did not wrap correctly, either too narrow or too wide, and some menus that behaved oddly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Via their website, Accordance offer a variety of bundles, I assume that with an account you could unlock these within the app but this is unclear. There are a small number of translations available individually for standard pricing. The bundles are expensive, the cheapest one with anything &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; out of copyright is USD 200. Ouch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;she-reads-truth&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/RXml1.i&quot;&gt;She Reads Truth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app is heavily focused around “quiet time” study guides. It offers a few translations for free, such as the ESV and NIV, but doesn’t offer any others for purchase. Unfortunately this app isn’t optimised for the large iPad and doesn’t support an inter-app split, although the studies can be split with the Bible text. Bizarrely the ones I tried took a large section of the screen up for a header image that I couldn’t seem to scroll away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does have a heavy focus on individual and community study with journaling and comments. This is interesting and different from all the other apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pocket-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/qbbdA.i&quot;&gt;Pocket Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app comes with the KJV and making an account gives you access to more, but it isn’t as visually slick as some of the other big commercial apps. There are some buttons that don’t seem to to anything, and others buttons that only work sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It supports splitting with other apps and &lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt; internal splits, which is impressive. It also offers some out-of-copyright commentaries and books. You’ll need to make purchases via their website, rather than through the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indies&quot;&gt;Indies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;touch-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/49mZH.i&quot;&gt;Touch Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Bible app comes with the standard free translations, and supports iPad split screen. The “loaded” version seems to come with a lot of extra resources, such as maps and commentaries, presumably also free or open license ones. Sadly this app doesn’t have an internal split or column options, and has one of the ugliest and most confusing interfaces of all these apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;holy-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/TnBzr.i&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourites on iPhone, this is my preferred way to view the NET. This app also offers an extensive collection of out-of-copyright resources. It can be internally split with up to four columns of Bibles or notes. Unfortunately you can’t split it with any of the study tools or the NET notes. The NET notes also aren’t viewable as footnotes in the text and have to be opened from the verse context menu. It does support iPad split screen, but that has some layout bugs when it’s on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paid-up-front&quot;&gt;Paid Up Front&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of interesting apps which are paid. I’m outlining some of them here, but note that I haven’t tried any of them. These are just ones that seem to offer something not provided by the apps above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;esword-hd&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/3T9YH.i&quot;&gt;eSword HD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app doesn’t look particularly beautiful, but if you enjoy and are committed to eSword for PC, this is one to consider. It supports splitting internally and with other apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;niv-audio-bible-read-by-david-suchet&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/L2Xh6.i&quot;&gt;NIV Audio Bible read by David Suchet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary focus of this app is the audio Bible recorded by actor David Suchet. If you’d like to try the audio out to see if you like it, get a sample of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itun.es/au/FE2zL.l&quot;&gt;“enhanced” NIV&lt;/a&gt; from the iBooks store. This uses the Anglicised text of the NIV (i.e. UK spelling), and has an internal split with your own notes. If you have a 16GB iPad, be warned that this app is almost 1.5GB because of the 80 hours of included audio. It isn’t available in the US or Canadian stores for copyright reasons but…. I’m sure that you can find a way around that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a version of this Bible without the audio called &lt;a href=&quot;https://appsto.re/au/XsSY6.i&quot;&gt;NIV Bible: British Text New International Version&lt;/a&gt;, which can use the audio from your iTunes library if you have the CD or iTunes audio book version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-app-purchases-direct-buying-and-bundles&quot;&gt;In-App Purchases, Direct Buying, and Bundles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these apps offer a dizzying array of ways to buy extra content. Some can be bought from a store within the app, some from the app’s website. Some apps offer bundles with multiple translations, commentaries, dictionaries, and maps. It’s hard to decide which offers the best value, and when you might be shelling out hundreds of dollars that can be a tough choice. If you’re &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; a student, then you’re probably going to want to be extra-sure that what you buy is worthwhile and at the best price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying via in-app purchase is the easiest way to buy. No need to break out the credit card, just your iTunes password. Depending on what currency you buy in it may actually be cheaper. For example, consider the NRSV in OliveTree. It’s AUD 14.99 in the app, and USD 9.99 on the website. In AUD at current market rates that’s $13.16, then add 6% for bank fees (yes, I hate them too) for $13.95. That seems pretty close, but I can get iTunes gift cards for 20% off at a local stationery shop so in-app wins handily, dropping to just $11.99&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. As a result it is important to note that only Olive Tree seems to offer all its books via in-app purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also bundles available for most apps. These typically include a selection of translations and resources at a discount to what you would pay if you bought them all individually. However, it’s important to check what actually makes up the bundle. Many of the lower-priced bundles are just collections of out-of-copyright works, and many of the higher priced bundles which claim ‘hundreds of resources’ for ‘thousands less’ are also padding out their packages with older books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a much better idea to start by looking at what books you would like &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; seeing if any bundle gives you a better deal than buying each alone. Try not to be tempted by things you don’t actually need. Some bundles may also come with a copy of the PC or Mac version of the software, which you may find useful. Use the free trial before committing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When buying individual books, you might be worried by how much of what you’re paying gets taken by intermediaries. Apple takes a 30% cut of one-off sales, and then the app publisher probably takes a slice, and then the book publisher, and finally the author. But this is true no matter how you buy the book, unless you can buy an ePub book or eSword resource directly from the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably also noticed the large number of versions of Logos, Tecarta and OliveTree which are paid up-front and come with Bible translations or resources included. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; these are primarily for gifting, since you can’t gift an in-app purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-recommendation&quot;&gt;A Recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking at so many apps, I was hoping to find a clear winner, or even better a number of high quality apps that offered all I wanted. Sadly every app has things I’m not happy with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the highest quality and largest variety of extra resources, I think the OliveTree app is worth serious consideration. If you’re addicted to the iPad split-screen and are happy to buy in USD, then Logos might edge it out. If you’re not so interested in academic commentaries, but are looking for a more personal study experience, try She Reads Truth. If you mainly read on your phone and just want your notes synced, go for the Youversion app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now I will probably use the OliveTree app when I need a variety of translations or a reference book, and I might keep Logos  or Holy Bible around just to use in split screen with other apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-app&quot;&gt;No App?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget that you don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to use an all-in-one Bible app. You can use sites like BibleGateway or the sites for individual translations to access the texts. Many resources are available through iBooks, Amazon, or Kobo. Some are even sold with no DRM direct from the publisher. Out-of-copyright works should be available free. You can use the iBooks app in split screen with Safari, or Notes, or any other writing application you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This solution does mean that you won’t have the notes in sync with the Bible text, and you’ll have to use pages of contents rather than nice chapter pickers. But you can then use just about any translation, resource book, or note taking app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You seem to be able to create new untitled sermon documents, and view synced ones from the desktop software, but not edit them. Not even the new ones you make in the app! Very strange. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bizarrely these themes are labeled “male” and “female”. I’m not sure what’s gendered about the themes but I fear this is shorthand for blue and pink. You can’t actually tell without buying them. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This might seem like an unfair inclusion, since gift cards can only be bought at certain price points so I’d surely be paying $15 for the smallest card. But I also have an Apple Music subscription and pay for iCloud storage, so I regularly buy iTunes cards on sale. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are finding choosing a baffling ordeal, then ask around. Friends, pastors, teachers, family. Even if they’ve only tried one commentary or two translations, you can ask if they still use it. And remember you don’t have to stick with one translation in English! You can use one for reference, one for church, one for reading aloud, one for reading long passages… in fact I think the more the better! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2016/10/08/bibles-for-ipad.html&quot;&gt;iPad Bibles - Study Time&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on October 08, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A User's Guide to OAuth 2.0]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2015/06/28/oauth2.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2015/06/28/oauth2</id>
  <published>2015-06-28T01:26:10+10:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-28T01:26:10+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;http://oauth.net/2/&quot;&gt;OAuth 2&lt;/a&gt; for a while now, and it seems every few months there’s a big kerfuffle because some provider or app has done OAuth 2 wrong, and left themselves open to exploitation. For the most part, I think these are mistakes where people just didn’t think, and there’s lots of room in the OAuth 2 spec to make bad mistakes. Really bad mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is part one of a two-part guide to OAuth 2. Part one covers accessing an OAuth 2 service, part two will cover providing an OAuth 2 service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-the-flow&quot;&gt;In the flow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; ways to authenticate to an OAuth 2 API, and your provider may support one or more of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authorization Code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implicit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resource Owner Password&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Client Credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can only use the first and the last. Even if your provider supports the others, don’t use them. The implicit grant is too easy to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack&quot;&gt;man-in-the-middle&lt;/a&gt;, and the third involves the user giving you their password, defeating the point of OAuth 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client credentials grant is used for accessing APIs where your service or app needs to be authenticated but you aren’t accessing APIs related to the user. An example would be a search endpoint, or a public user profile url. It uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_access_authentication&quot;&gt;BASIC Auth&lt;/a&gt; to just pass your client credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;authorization-code&quot;&gt;Authorization Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first flow is the one you’ll use almost all the time. I’ll explain it with an analogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You start at a new job and need to get a swipe card for the door. In order to get the swipe card, you go to security and get a form, which your manager has to sign to say which doors you can access, and when you can use it. Your manager signs to say you can have access to the front and back doors, between 8:00 and 18:00, but not on weekends. You take the form back to security, and security issue you a pass with an expiry in one year. They tell you if you come back within a month of it expiring, they can issue you with a new one without having to get the form signed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this story, your app or website is you; the user is your manager; the authorization code is the form; security is the OAuth 2 service. Your app needs access to a user’s data, so the first step is to make an authorization request using your client credentials to the OAuth 2 service. Then you can direct the user to the service’s site, and they can authorize your app to access certain resources. You’ll get a redirect from the service to your website with an authorization code. Your app or site can then exchange the authorization code for an access token, and possibly a refresh token. The access token will only last for a certain while, and when it expires you can use the refresh token to get a new access token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be aware that the authorization code and the access token are &lt;em&gt;single use&lt;/em&gt;. If you have a failure of some kind, you’ll need to start the authorization process again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-detail&quot;&gt;In Detail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Register your client with your OAuth 2 provider. You will be issued some credentials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;obey-the-rules-for-your-protection&quot;&gt;Obey the rules for your protection&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you have to do is read the rules of your API provider. If you’re using a large provider like Google, Facebook, or Twitter, they will provide example code even whole toolkits and frameworks. Use them. If your provider recommends a library, use it. If you’re on desktop or mobile and there’s a &lt;em&gt;system API&lt;/em&gt; to use instead, use it. Save yourself work and heartache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side: don’t trust your provider. If you’re using a library or framework with a mobile app, check how it works. Make sure it’s keeping to best practice, because these things are not always well-maintained. Understand what it’s doing, when, and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;https-or-bust&quot;&gt;HTTPS or Bust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All communications that you are involved in over the network must be encrypted. I can’t emphasize this enough, if you can’t do https, you can’t do oAuth 2, and really you shouldn’t be doing anything authenticated at all. Any provider worth their salt will only provide https endpoints, and will refuse to redirect to any non-https website. For the moment, this means &lt;a href=&quot;http://help.squarespace.com/guides/does-squarespace-support-ssl-access&quot;&gt;no Squarespace&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://konklone.com/post/github-pages-now-sorta-supports-https-so-use-it&quot;&gt;no GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. SSL certificates can be bought for as little as $10 USD a year. Your hosting will be more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another part of this is you must use a ‘real’ https url, at your site or your providers, for all callbacks. Some providers give you the option of out-of-band (oob) callbacks, where rather than issuing a redirect to your website, the provider shows the user a code to copy. If you use that option, great. Otherwise &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; use https.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;access-tokens-are-sacred&quot;&gt;Access Tokens are Sacred&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to protect your access tokens and refresh tokens, how you protect them depends on how your service works. If you have a website, do not store the access token in a cookie. Store it in a database on the server, and lock down your database. Make sure your database is safe from SQL injections which might steal the tokens. Use multiple database users with restricted permissions, so parts of the code doing, say, stats logging, don’t have access to the user tokens table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are making a desktop or mobile client, do not store the token in plain text in a config file. Store it in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keychain_(software)&quot;&gt;keychain&lt;/a&gt; on Mac and iOS, in an Android app encrypt the tokens with a RSA public key and store the matching private key in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.androidauthority.com/where-is-the-best-place-to-store-a-password-in-your-android-app-597197/&quot;&gt;keystore&lt;/a&gt;. On Windows &lt;a href=&quot;http://weblogs.asp.net/jongalloway//encrypting-passwords-in-a-net-app-config-file&quot;&gt;encrypt it&lt;/a&gt;, on Linux, encrypt the password with a private key and keep the private key &lt;a href=&quot;http://superuser.com/questions/578295/where-to-store-openssl-private-keys-on-linux-server&quot;&gt;appropriately stored&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;client-credentials-are-your-password&quot;&gt;Client Credentials are Your Password&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you leave the password to your server database in plain text in a config file for your mobile app? Would you put it in the JavaScript on your page?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Then don’t do it with your client credentials. If someone else uses your client credentials then they can impersonate you to the service. With something like Twitter or Google which has API limits (which you could even be paying for), you really need to make sure you’re the only one using them. You probably won’t be able to encrypt your credentials, but at least put some effort in to obfuscate them, and keep an eye on their use. You might need to revoke them if someone else starts using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If your answer is yes, please stop doing anything with passwords or authentication. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2015/06/28/oauth2.html&quot;&gt;A User's Guide to OAuth 2.0&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on June 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A (Baker's) Dozen Drawings]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2015/04/28/drawing-roundup.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2015/04/28/drawing-roundup</id>
  <published>2015-04-28T01:26:10+10:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-28T01:26:10+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to become a digital artist since I first had my own computer, banging around in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kid_Pix&quot;&gt;Kid Pix&lt;/a&gt;. But since art has never been my profession (and to be honest I’m not good enough or dedicated enough) I’ve never been able to shell out for the pro tools: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wacom.com/en-us/products/pen-displays/cintiq-22-hd&quot;&gt;Wacom Cintiqs&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve often used things designed for other purposes: PCs, iPads, even game consoles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve chosen to illustrate my attempts to (mis)use these tools with a series of drawings of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.serebii.net/pokedex-dp/152.shtml&quot;&gt;Chikorita&lt;/a&gt;. Try not to laugh too hard and spill your drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clockwise from bottom left: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nintendo_3DS#Larger_model&quot;&gt;3DS XL&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wii_U_GamePad&quot;&gt;Wii U Gamepad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://au.pcmag.com/wacom-intuos-creative-stylus/714/review/wacom-intuos-creative-stylus&quot;&gt;Wacom Creative Stylus&lt;/a&gt; (for iPad), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnet.com/products/wacom-graphire3/&quot;&gt;Wacom Graphire 3&lt;/a&gt;, custom resistive stylus made from a chopstick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graphics-tablet--laptop&quot;&gt;Graphics Tablet + Laptop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first got my Wacom tablet back in 2003 or so. It replaced my mouse after I did in my mouse arm playing too many games. I loved, I still love, that battered purple thing. I messed around with my Linux kernel trying to get the pressure sensitivity to work in The GIMP for ages. Now of course you just tick a couple of boxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need a good ergonomic set-up with a computer and a Wacom tablet. I did these paintings sitting on the couch, with my Wacom connected to my laptop, my laptop beside me, and a cat on my lap. I really wouldn’t recommend it (the cat is nice, the neck pain is not). I’ve tried a desk and monitor approach, which is much more ergonomic, but I don’t have that at home right now, and it’s certainly not portable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have problem with the distance. It’s okay as a mouse replacement, or for doing a bit of layout or simple work. But I just don’t seem to be able to think in the right way. I’m never sure how the mapping works, how much movement on the tablet will produce how much on the screen. I cope better with a smaller screen; my huge 27” monitor at work mapped to my tiny work Bamboo is a joke, but even on a 13” laptop screen I struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, it’s great for those times when I need something better than a trackpad, and if you’re working at a computer anyway, that’s fine. It’s just me that’s the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gimp-free&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gimp.org&quot;&gt;The GIMP&lt;/a&gt; (free)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/MacTheGimp.png&quot; alt=&quot;The GIMP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GIMP is a strange beast. It tries to be Photoshop, without Photoshop’s massive cash-flows. In some ways, it’s like a weird knock-off, but if it is, it’s the weird knock-off that I’ve known for ten years. It feels like having a soft spot for Home Brand pizza cheese, you don’t want to admit it in polite company but secretly you eat it by the handful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corel-painter-lite&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.painterartist.com/us/product/photo-effects/&quot;&gt;Corel Painter Lite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/MacCorelPainter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Corel Painter Lite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m relatively new to Corel Painter, having picked up the Lite version in some promo or bundle. It’s a lot nicer than The GIMP for traditional-style painting, even this cut-down version. I think I got a licence for Procreate Painter Classic (not to be confused with Procreate for iPad) with my Wacom a long time ago, and I’m 90% sure they’re the same thing. It’s a bit hard to tell as Painter Classic is on disk (I have no disk drive) and is &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBook#iBook_G4_.28.22Snow.22.29&quot;&gt;PowerPC only&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ipad--capacitive-stylus&quot;&gt;iPad + Capacitive Stylus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve owned a few iPad styluses since I first got my old original iPad (and replaced it, poor thing). I’m currently using a Wacom Creative Stylus (the original, not the 2), which is absolutely the best capacitive stylus I’ve ever used. Which is to say it’s like the rubber end of a pencil to paint on glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over my years with the iPad, I’ve collected quite a few painting and drawing apps. I’m going to start with the ones I like least, which doesn’t mean they’re rubbish, they just aren’t for me. Most don’t fully support my Wacom stylus, so no pressure sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;auryn-ink&quot;&gt;Auryn Ink&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadAurynInk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Auryn Ink&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find Auryn Ink very baffling. I never know how to make the buttons come back. I don’t understand why it only has one level of undo. I’m not sure when my paint will mix or has dried. I don’t think it has layers. This is illustrated in my terrible painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;colors&quot;&gt;Colors!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadColors!.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colors!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing and painting in Colors! is very jaggy. I like that the tools keep it simple, but I find it impossible to get a smooth line. I only keep this app around because it is the easiest way to get pictures from Colors! 3D onto my iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paper-by-53&quot;&gt;Paper by 53&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadPaper53.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paper by 53&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper by 53 is a cool-looking sketchbook, but I find the gestures infuriating. Undo, damn you, undo! I also don’t like being stuck with one size of each brush, or without layers. What I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; like are the colour palettes. They’ve now made the colour mixer free, but I’ve barely touched it, because the palettes are so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;artrage&quot;&gt;ArtRage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadArtRage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ArtRage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really want to love ArtRage, but it is just unbelievably slow. I’m running it on an iPad Air, and the lag is bad. Especially with the smudge tools. Sometimes the smudge tools don’t even load, the app just does nothing when I use them. I haven’t used it with the pressure sensitivity, because that will only make the lag worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an app with great potential, but it lacks the polish of its desktop kin. The tools are good fun, all highly customisable, and I like the pen smoothing a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adobe-ideas&quot;&gt;Adobe Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadAdobeIdeas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Adobe Ideas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, this app has been discontinued. Every time I start it up it tells me I should migrate to Adobe Sketches. No chance. Adobe Sketches has an infuriating gesture-based interface. Adobe Ideas is slick and smooth. It supports palettes (although it comes with none), it has a nice selection of tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference with this app is it’s not really a painting app, it’s a vector app. Not a dragging-points-and-curves style vector app, but a drawing app. You can export your work to PDF and blow it up huge! But don’t, then you will see all your mistakes. The nature of this app means there’s no blend tool, which is a tool I use a lot, but that’s okay. I’m okay with what this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sketches&quot;&gt;Sketches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadSketches.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketches&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketches is what I wanted Paper to be. It supports my stylus, it has variable brush sizes, it has layers. It also has some infuriating gestures, but undo is mapped to my stylus button and the tools are always on screen, so I can cope. It has a nice default palette. Sketches is my go-to sketchbook app, which I guess is the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;procreate&quot;&gt;Procreate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/iPadProcreate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Procreate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, Procreate. What can I say? You can zoom and twist to angle the painting. You can cut and paste. Custom brushes. Palettes. &lt;em&gt;Export to PSD&lt;/em&gt;. Layer blend modes. This is the absolute best iPad painting app. I love it dearly. Every time I stray to another app, thinking its cool new style will win me over, I come back to Procreate. More than any other software or hardware I have bought this has paid for itself over and over. This app is worth well over $50, more like $200, but it’s just $7.50. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/procreate-sketch-paint-create./id425073498?mt=8&quot;&gt;Buy it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But. It is let down by the hardware. Even a really good capacitive stylus is fat and rubbery and imprecise. I just cannot get a smooth line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3ds&quot;&gt;3DS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;colors-3d&quot;&gt;Colors! 3D&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/3DSColors!3D.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colors! 3D&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first got this app, I was happy drawing away. It’s so much easier on a resistive touch screen, even the tiny 3DS one. But the colour on the 3DS screen and the resolution mean that it just doesn’t work. Look at this picture! It looked smooth, with nicely erased edges on the 3DS screen, but when exported you get to see what it really is. Really ugly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see my other Colors! and Colors! 3D paintings on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://colorslive.com/author?id=142272&quot;&gt;Colors! Gallery profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pokemon-art-academy&quot;&gt;Pokemon Art Academy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/3DSPokemonArtAcademy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pokemon Art Academy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pokemon Art Academy is more of a light teaching tool than a painting app, but you can paint anything you like in free mode. However, it is limited in its export options, they’re low resolution, it always puts a watermark over everything you do, and all the exported pictures have terrible jpeg artefacts. It has nice tools, with one layer for inking and one for drawing and painting. The inking pen has even smoothing, and the pastels and paints have a good texture. But this game is also limited by the same things as Colors! 3D: the poor screen quality on the 3Ds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see all the pictures I’ve done so far on &lt;a href=&quot;https://miiverse.nintendo.net/users/lupiter/posts&quot;&gt;Miiverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wii-u&quot;&gt;Wii U&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;art-academy-sketchpad&quot;&gt;Art Academy Sketchpad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/WiiUArtAcademySketchPad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Art Academy Sketchpad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screen quality on the Wii U tablet is much better, but sadly the application isn’t. There’s no layers, you can just ‘fix’ your work at any stage to make it non-erasable. There’s &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; undo, which is baffling and irritating. So often I would switch tools and forget to change the pen size, and end up with giant pastel marks when I’d planned for tiny, and only an eraser to remove them. I get that this is trying to be “real”, but it’s completely missed the advantages of digital art in its slavery to the media it apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This application also lacks export options. You can’t export to the SD card, or share via wifi, the only export option is to Miiverse. It only has two levels of zoom, 100% and 200%. It doesn’t have any inking or smoothing, just pencils and pastels. It was released in August of 2013 with two of the four main menu items saying “Coming Soon!” and… they haven’t been released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But. But. The resistive screen is &lt;em&gt;so much better&lt;/em&gt; than a capacitive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also drawn &lt;a href=&quot;https://miiverse.nintendo.net/posts/AYQHAAABAAAtVHhl3CYHzg&quot;&gt;Woobat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://miiverse.nintendo.net/posts/AYQHAAABAACNUKFE3fjL-A&quot;&gt;Bergamite&lt;/a&gt; (although I wrongly posted them to the my SO’s account).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paper--pencil&quot;&gt;Paper &amp;amp; Pencil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to prove I’m not as bad as some of these pictures might suggest, here’s a quick sketch I did with pencil and paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/chikorita/paperAndPencil.png&quot; alt=&quot;Paper &amp;amp; Derwent Studio Pencils&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not great, but better than all my digital versions, alas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It appears Corel Painter Lite is no longer, or possibly never has been, available to buy. The link is for Corel Painter Essentials, USD$50 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2015/04/28/drawing-roundup.html&quot;&gt;A (Baker's) Dozen Drawings&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on April 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bibles on iPhone: Free 2 Pray Editions]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2014/09/15/bible-roundup.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2014/09/15/bible-roundup</id>
  <published>2014-09-15T01:26:10+10:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-15T01:26:10+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of Bible apps out there, and like the rest of the App Store, the majority are ugly garbage. But that doesn’t mean a kid on an iTouch needs to be stuck with a King James in Comic Sans. I’ve looked at 19&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Bible apps, to try and cut out some of the chaff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What app is most suitable for you will depend on where, how, and why you want to read the Bible. If you have an iPod Touch, or a low data limit, you’ll want a Bible app with offline translations. If you’re a Bible College student, you might want an app with side-by-side with Greek. If you’re a nitpicker, you might want two translations side-by-side. Or Study notes. Or translators’ notes. Or you might need a big font, or a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serif&quot;&gt;serif&lt;/a&gt; font. I’ve tried to pick out five apps that I think will have most people covered, and point out why you might be interested in some of the others instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the publishers of these apps also have apps dedicated to a particular translation. As far as I can see, these are just the same as buying in-app, and if you get the ‘master’ app you can then try some of the translations out before paying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, you can always have more than one Bible app!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h6 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h6&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Choosing a Bible translation is a very personal decision, and one I’m going to stay clear of here. If you want help picking a translation, try them all. Ask your friends, pastor, elders, minister, scholar, or priest. Don’t just read nobodies on the internet frothing at the mouth about them, many of whom say wildly contradictory things.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Checkout the table at the bottom for which Bible apps carry which translations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;top-picks&quot;&gt;Top Picks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-peoples-choice-bible&quot;&gt;The People’s Choice: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible/id282935706?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/Bible-YouVersion.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bible by LifeChurch.tv&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone says they have “the Bible app” on their iPhone, they almost certainly mean they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible/id282935706?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible&lt;/a&gt; by YouVersion/LifeChurch.tv. It has a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of translations, all of which are free, many of which are available to download for offline use. There are no ads, it’s well updated, and it runs on anything that can run &lt;a href=&quot;http://support.apple.com/kb/DL1578?viewlocale=en_US&amp;amp;locale=en_US&quot;&gt;iOS 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downsides to this app are that it really pushes its reading plans, and that you need an account to download Bibles for offline reading. Sometimes those downloads require you to share your email address with the publisher, so the publisher might annoy you (although I’ve not noticed this happening). I have a different reading plan, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordlive.org/Session&quot;&gt;WordLive&lt;/a&gt; via RSS, so I’m not keen on the push toward reading plans, since I mainly use a Bible app for quick lookups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lightweight-bible-reader&quot;&gt;The Lightweight: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-reader-bibles.org/id738007515?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible Reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/Bible-Reader.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bible Reader - Bibles.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If storage is a premium, but reception and data aren’t, then you might want to look here. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-reader-bibles.org/id738007515?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible Reader&lt;/a&gt; from the American Bible Society is less than 15MB (some Bible apps come in at over 200MB), and has a decent selection of translations for free. It’s easy to use and light on the eyes, but it doesn’t have any note taking or highlighting features, so it’s strictly for &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-indie-holy-bible&quot;&gt;The Indie: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/holy-bible/id291877741?mt=8&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/HolyBible.png&quot; alt=&quot;Holy Bible&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/holy-bible/id291877741?mt=8&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/a&gt; is made by a missionary, Paul Avery, in his spare time. That a side project can compete with the big names in Bibles says a lot about how much care Paul has put into this Bible app. While this only has translations with liberal copyright (or out of copyright), it is very easy to use. Holy Bible lets you view up to five sources (Bibles or notes) side-by-side. You can also buy some study guides in the app, and for a very modest sum you can also get the NET notes (without which I think the NET is not complete).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have encountered a very few minor issues, but this app is much slicker, more customizable, and easy to use than YouVersion. Unlike Bible Reader it has offline support and note-taking. If NET and WEB (and ESV online) are enough modern translations for you, then consider supporting the little guy (and buying an IAP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-study-bible-collection-tecarta-bible&quot;&gt;The Study Bible Collection: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/tecarta-bible/id325955298?mt=8&quot;&gt;Tecarta Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/Tecarta-Bible.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tecarta Bible&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, you might think that Tecarta’s offering is a slightly nicer YouVersion where you have to pay for the Bible translations, but Tecarta have quite a selection of Study and Devotional Bibles that you might remember from a book shop. These Study Bibles are mostly NIV and NKJV Bibles and cost less than $20 (unlike some other app’s Study Bibles) but if you want some notes from Max Lucado, then this might be the place for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-integrated-system-bible-and-faithlife-study-bible&quot;&gt;The Integrated System: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible!/id336400266?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible!&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/faithlife-study-bible/id485998842?mt=8&quot;&gt;Faithlife Study Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/Bible-Logos.png&quot; alt=&quot;Logos Bible&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure that Bible! used to be known as Logos Bible. It’s also almost the same as the Faithlife Study Bible, but it appears that Bible! has more available translations, and Faithlife has no option to skip making an account. Bible! doesn’t make you have an account, but the store will appear empty if you aren’t logged in. This Bible app can be used to sync your reading with your church sermon, if they use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://proclaimonline.com/&quot;&gt;Proclaim&lt;/a&gt; presentation software. It also has a built-in social network, where you can have a private group like a Bible study where you can share notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logos are a long-running and well-known provider of digital Bibles. As such, in addition to quite a range of translations they have a lot of really serious study tools, like all 26 volumes of Barnes’ Notes on the Old and New Testaments. However be prepared to pay close to what you’d pay for a paper copy, even for the King James Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-choices&quot;&gt;Other Choices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bible-study-with-accordance&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-study-with-accordance/id411970514?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible Study with Accordance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Has a lot of academic resources, lets you view two Bibles side-by-side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Not very nice to use, Bibles are priced the same (or more expensive) than the paper versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bible-1-and-bible-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-+1/id376874469?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible +1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-*/id465455201?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible *&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two are 100% identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Nice looking, good range of translations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Some translations can’t be ‘trialled’, no free offline translations (not even KJV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibleis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible.is/id378075859?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible.is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Has dramatic readings of all available translations, which can be downloaded and used offline in addition to the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: A bit clunky to use, heavily focused on audio Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bible-gateway&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-gateway/id506512797?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible Gateway&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: All bibles are free, some available offline, can sync with your Bible Gateway account, some audio Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Buttons are very small, has ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible+/id332615624?mt=8&quot;&gt;Bible+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Has one of the widest ranges of Bibles, including Greek interlinears and other specialty Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Has an odd fake-book look, and can be a bit fiddly to navigate. The specialty Bibles are very expensive, but that’s true of the paper version too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mantis-bible-study&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/mantis-bible-study/id286041914?mt=8&quot;&gt;Mantis Bible Study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Works on iOS 4.3 and later, so runs on older devices like the 2nd generation iPod Touch or the iPhone 3G. Possibly the only source of the ‘84 NIV (I haven’t paid to check, but the copyright suggests it might be the old one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Seriously visually outdated, doesn’t have retina graphics (looks jaggy), Bibles are paperback price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ebible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-from-ebible.com-niv/id476231051?mt=8&quot;&gt;eBible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Tries to look like the old iBooks, has a small range of okay priced Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Tries to look like the old iBooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;esv-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/esv-bible/id361797273?mt=8&quot;&gt;ESV Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Good taster for the ESV Study Bible (if you like the ESV), easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Only has the ESV, look and feel is a bit of a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;glo-bible-bible--for-iphone&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/bible-for-iphone/id435113532?mt=8&quot;&gt;Glo Bible&lt;/a&gt; (Bible ⊹ for iPhone)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: Has a good selection of maps, videos and other resources, and the upgrade is a bundle. Very powerful multiple ‘sessions’ where you can have different passages or resources open and cross-check them. Includes the NIV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Is a bit tricky to use, not the prettiest if you don’t like black. I couldn’t find out how to subscribe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;holy-bible-free&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/holy-bible-free*/id528947242?mt=8&quot;&gt;Holy Bible Free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: You like the icon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: It’s not that pretty, it has ads, limited selection of older Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pocketsword&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/pocketsword/id341046078?mt=8&quot;&gt;PocketSword&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crosswire.org/forums/mvnforum/viewthread_thread,795&quot;&gt;side-load&lt;/a&gt; Bibles in the Sword format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: Visually outdated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simple-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/simple-bible/id378238628?mt=8&quot;&gt;Simple Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: If you think all translations since the KJV are rubbish and don’t want to even have the option of downloading them. It’s easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: You like a more modern translation, you like something that looks nicer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wordsearch-bible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/wordsearch-bible/id484607082?mt=8&quot;&gt;WORDSearch Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might like it: If you like the HCSB, and it has a selection of non-Bible Christian books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why you might not like it: If you don’t love the HCSB, and the store is very tricky to navigate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-20&quot;&gt;Option 20&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one major option I’ve not covered here, and that’s getting an eBook of your favourite translation from the iBooks store. I’ve left it until now for a few reasons. The first is that not that many translations are on the iBooks store (for example, it doesn’t have the CEV), and even when they are the quality can be quite poor&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They can also be a lot more expensive than the in-app Bibles. The NRSV ranges from $6.50 to $50 as in IAP, but $14-$18 in the iBooks Store. The NIV is between Free and $50 in app, and from around $10 to $30 (for study Bibles) in the iBooks store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, ePubs of Bibles can be quite unwieldy. I do have an ePub of the NET with notes, and as originally delivered (a single book) it was incredibly slow to turn pages and find chapters. It was so slow to go to any of the footnotes and back as to be completely unusable. I then broke it into individual books and fixed a lot of typesetting errors, which makes it fast enough that I can get to a reference before the end of the reading. This was quite hard and involved building a special program to do it. Thankfully I didn’t buy the ePub through the iBooks store, where some books have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/ebooks/comments/1ljvi2/ibooks_and_drm_removal/&quot;&gt;DRM&lt;/a&gt; which would prevent this kind of fix. There’s no way to tell which books in the iBooks store have DRM, it’s buy and hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In favour of the eBooks is that this can be the cheapest (or only) way to get some study Bibles electronically. If you really want your “NIV Stewardship Study Bible” or “Spirit-Filled Life Bible For Women” on your phone, this may be your only choice. Before shelling out though, get a sample and make sure it’s an okay eBook conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-check-box-table&quot;&gt;Feature Check-box Table&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table is huge, please scroll sideways for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Installed Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Company&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Version Reviewed&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Installed &amp;amp; Setup Size (MB)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Multiple Translations&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Works Offline&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Dark Mode&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Adjustable Font Size&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Adjustable Font&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Adjustable Spacing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse Formatting&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Daily Devotions&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Personal Notes&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Note Export Sync&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Sharing&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Audio&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Study with Accordance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Accordance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;OakTree Software Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.7.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;280&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line, paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dropbox, Account sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible (YouVersion)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;LifeChurch.tv&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;5.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;22.2 (45 with 1 offline bible)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;With Account&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;With Account&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Account sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tecarta Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tecarta, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;70.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line, paragraphs (depends on translation)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Account sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible * &amp;amp; Bible+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible* &amp;amp; Bible +1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Just1Word Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3.0.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;38.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible.is&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible.is&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Faith Comes by Hearing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2.5.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;28.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Gateway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Gateway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nelson Media Inc&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse of the day, reading plans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Reader - bibles.org&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Reader&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;American Bible Society&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.1.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;13.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Study&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nelson Media Inc&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;5.9.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;149&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Reading plans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mantis Bible Study&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible Study&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mantis Bible Company&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4.9.21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;29.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Reading plans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;eBible from eBible.com …&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;eBible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Ospirit Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;ESV Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;ESV Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Crossway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2.5.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;27.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Account sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible + for iPhone&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Glo Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Information Humanities Inc&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.4.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;153&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Reading plans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Account sync&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Holy Bible Free*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Teofilo Vizcaino&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2.1.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;39.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paul Avery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;8.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;23.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line, giant blob&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Reading plans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bible!&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Logos Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Logos Bible Software&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4.3.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;103&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Study guides&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;PocketSword&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;PocketSword&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nic Carter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.4.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;36.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Giant blob&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Simple Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Simple Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jolon Faichney&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.0.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;11.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Faithlife Study Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Study Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Logos Bible Software&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4.3.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;377&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;WORDSearch Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;WORDSearch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;LifeWay Christian Resources&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2.4.2139&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;161&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Verse-per-line, paragraphs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Available for purchase?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✔︎&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;✘&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;english-bible-translation-availability&quot;&gt;(English) Bible Translation Availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prices in this table are in AUD at the time of publication. They’re all likely to change a bit, but they should give you a rough idea of what to expect to pay or have available in these apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Bibles contain translations not in this table, especially translations which are out of copyright. I’ve tried to include the major translations, but if there’s one in particular you feel I’ve missed feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/sircathywise&quot;&gt;drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that ESV, Simple Bible, and WORDSearch Bible listed above both only have one translation, ESV, KJV and HCSB respectively, and so are excluded from the table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table is big, please scroll sideways for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lockman.org/amplified/&quot;&gt;AMP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible_in_Basic_English&quot;&gt;BBE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/Contemporary-English-Version-CEV-Bible/&quot;&gt;CEV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biblesociety.org.uk/the-bible/search-the-bible/CEVUK/&quot;&gt;CEV UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esv.org/esv/introduction/&quot;&gt;ESV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva_Bible&quot;&gt;GNV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biblestudytools.com/gw/&quot;&gt;GW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/Good-News-Translation-GNT-Bible/&quot;&gt;GNT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hcsb.org&quot;&gt;HCSB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_James_Version&quot;&gt;KJV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Message_(Bible)&quot;&gt;MSG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_American_Standard_Bible&quot;&gt;NASB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://netbible.com&quot;&gt;NET&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_International_Reader's_Version&quot;&gt;NIRV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biblestudytools.com/niv/&quot;&gt;NIV 84&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/New-International-Version-NIV-Bible/&quot;&gt;NIV 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/New-International-Version-UK-NIVUK-Bible/&quot;&gt;NIV UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_King_James_Version&quot;&gt;NKJV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newlivingtranslation.com&quot;&gt;NLT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrsv.net&quot;&gt;NRSV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revised_Standard_Version&quot;&gt;RSV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/Good-News-Translation-GNT-Bible/&quot;&gt;TEV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ebible.org/web/&quot;&gt;WEB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young's_Literal_Translation&quot;&gt;Young’s Literal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible Study with Accordance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$49.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$49.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$49.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$49.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tecarta Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$9.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$9.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$1.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible */Bible +1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$4.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$1.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$8.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible.is&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00 (NT)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00 (NT)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible Gateway&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible Reader - bibles.org&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mantis Bible Study&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$18.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$1.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$6.49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;eBible from eBible.com …&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$16.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$1.29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible + for iPhone&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Holy Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bible!&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;PocketSword&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Simple Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Faithlife Study Bible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$12.99&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I thought it was 20, but it turns out two of them are 100% identical, so I’m treating them as one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is actually a problem with eBooks in general. Far too often they’re made from a scan of a copy of the book, and full of errors that would be easily fixed by having a human editor. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2014/09/15/bible-roundup.html&quot;&gt;Bibles on iPhone: Free 2 Pray Editions&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on September 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Woman In Tech]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2014/03/25/woman-in-tech.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2014/03/25/woman-in-tech</id>
  <published>2014-03-25T06:28:10+11:00</published>
  <updated>2014-03-25T06:28:10+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a woman, and I work as a “software engineer”. I didn’t plan that, but looking back it should have been obvious that I’d really enjoy this. As far as I can remember I’ve always been interested in computers, as my parents were. But I had so many interests: art, music, writing, crafts, reading, science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when I was fifteen or so, my parents bought me a new computer for my birthday. They told me they went to the local computer shop (the kind that sell parts and always have faded paper signs), and bought the appropriate parts. The assistant asked if they’d like her to put it together for them, and my father replied that me getting to put it together was part of the present. And it was! I read all the instructions, and put it all together, and installed a fresh copy of Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my second year of high school we were offered a special credit IT subject, which would run across three years. Excited I joined up, one of two girls. The class consisted of copying out a dry textbook on computer architecture, and practical classes in Microsoft Word and Excel. Almost everyone dropped it as soon as we could. In my fourth year of high school I took a programming subject (again, one of two girls), where I learnt the basics of Java. My teacher was very enthusiastic, but not very good; I and two other students bothered to do any of the work, the rest played Quake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home, I devoured forums and man pages, I learnt how to use makefiles, and how to write HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t take any computer subjects for my final two years of high school, I’d given up. In my final year I took just four subjects: Chemistry, English, Japanese, and double Maths. I applied to study architecture at university. I got into architecture, but after a gap break, I decided to study Japanese instead. After six months of Japanese, I dropped it for… more maths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of my maths degree I had to take an introductory programming subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took more. I added a major in Computer Science. But I still saw my future in maths, in a PhD in pure maths, and academia. It wasn’t until a few things happened in my third and fourth years that I reassessed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I met someone doing a PhD in pure mathematics, and he told me how hard it was to get a ‘regular’ job with a PhD. I had to commit 100% to the academic life, if that was what I wanted. I had done some casual tutoring, which I found very draining: I didn’t want to be a lecturer. I also wasn’t sure I’d cut it, I was finding the courses a lot less interesting, and a lot harder to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then one of my programming lecturers offered me a summer job, making an update to some in-house software for another company he worked at. I didn’t know the language it was written in (PHP) or the framework. I’d never used a database, I’d never even written any SQL. But I realized: I was good at this, I was getting paid to be good at this, and it was &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve often wondered why, for so long, I’d been able to imagine myself in careers to do with all my other interests. A jeweler, a painter, an author, a flautist, a singer, an essayist, a translator, an architect, a professor. But not a “computer-er”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess it’s hard to imagine what you can’t see, and have never been taught about. I’d barely heard of programming as a career, and definitely not women coders. It’s doubly hard when school syllabuses for computing and programming are so rubbish. I really think, apart from computer literacy, if you’re not going (or able) to teach it well, better not to teach it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think programming is perhaps better taught to youngsters when they have a reason: to make a game, an app, fix an ebook, calculate something, make a nice graph, make a blog theme. And tell them that this is a great career choice.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2014/03/25/woman-in-tech.html&quot;&gt;A Woman In Tech&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on March 25, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying High]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2014/01/29/flying-high.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2014/01/29/flying-high</id>
  <published>2014-01-29T04:28:10+11:00</published>
  <updated>2014-01-29T04:28:10+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There’s been some recent brouhaha over how &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com.au/25-photos-from-golden-age-of-aviation-2013-7?op=1#passengers-aboard-a-boeing-747-enjoy-the-spacious-economy-class-configuration-date-unknown-24&quot;&gt;“air travel was exciting”&lt;/a&gt; and glamorous in the ’50s and ’60s. Which isn’t, of course, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052748704684604575380992283473182&quot;&gt;new complaint&lt;/a&gt;. But it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcodesign.com/3022215/terminal-velocity/what-it-was-really-like-to-fly-during-the-golden-age-of-travel#3&quot;&gt;rubbish&lt;/a&gt;. It was boring, smoky, dangerous, noisy, and drunken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the legroom! The &lt;a href=&quot;http://s.wsj.net/public/resources/images/PJ-AW097_MIDSEA_DV_20100721200627.jpg&quot;&gt;touch of class&lt;/a&gt;! Airport queues were not an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/news/tsa&quot;&gt;ordeal&lt;/a&gt;. Well, actually, you can have that now. But let me take you on a little trip first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sydney-to-london&quot;&gt;Sydney to London&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is Monday December 1st, 1947 and a QANTAS &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lockheed_Constellation&quot;&gt;Lockheed Constellation&lt;/a&gt; is preparing to leave Sydney airport. Its destination is London, via the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kangaroo_Route&quot;&gt;Kangaroo Route&lt;/a&gt;. This is the first time a ‘direct’ flight has been available from Sydney to London. Before now, QANTAS flew to Singapore, and from there you could take an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/qf39&quot;&gt;Empire Airways&lt;/a&gt; flight to London. Today there are just 29 passengers, and 11 crew, and they’re leaving at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/qf48/qf48-2.jpg&quot;&gt;22.30&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take them nearly four days. You see, the plane can’t fly well at night, and it needs to refuel regularly. So they’ll be stopping in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin,_Northern_Territory&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singapore&quot;&gt;Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karachi&quot;&gt;Karachi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo&quot;&gt;Cairo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castel_Benito&quot;&gt;Castel Benito&lt;/a&gt; (Tripoli), and London. They’ll spend the nights in Singapore, Karachi, and Cairo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years later, in 1953, this same trip will be leaving &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/qf53/qf53-2.jpg&quot;&gt;every day except Sunday&lt;/a&gt; and cost &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/qf53/qf53-6.jpg&quot;&gt;£529 4s&lt;/a&gt; (that’s British pounds, not Australian). The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/dc-3/vh-anh/vhanh.html&quot;&gt;cabin&lt;/a&gt; looks rather like a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/brandon301095/6837910940/&quot;&gt;Dash-8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flight cost of just £529 4s? Well, that’s in 1953. That’s equivalent to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.measuringworth.com/ppoweruk/result.php?use%5B%5D=CPI&amp;amp;use%5B%5D=NOMINALEARN&amp;amp;year_early=1953&amp;amp;pound71=529&amp;amp;shilling71=4&amp;amp;pence71=&amp;amp;amount=529.2&amp;amp;year_source=1953&amp;amp;year_result=2012&quot;&gt;£12,500&lt;/a&gt; today, equal to $23,650 AUD, or $20,750 USD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so not many people could pay that! Clearly only the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/l-1049/vh-eaf/1802.072.html&quot;&gt;Queen&lt;/a&gt; and other &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/l-1049/vh-eag/1802.084.html&quot;&gt;VIPs&lt;/a&gt; were flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/l-1049/vh-eag/1802.084.html&quot;&gt;1963&lt;/a&gt; there were two classes, and flying the much improved &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/b-707q/vh-eba/4604.846.html&quot;&gt;Boeing 707 Jet&lt;/a&gt; the flight time was down to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/qf63/qf63-03.jpg&quot;&gt;less than two days&lt;/a&gt;, since no overnight stops were required. But the price of a return Economy ticket was still high at £471.40, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.measuringworth.com/ppoweruk/result.php?use%5B%5D=CPI&amp;amp;use%5B%5D=NOMINALEARN&amp;amp;year_early=1963&amp;amp;pound71=471&amp;amp;shilling71=4&amp;amp;pence71=&amp;amp;amount=471.2&amp;amp;year_source=1963&amp;amp;year_result=2012&quot;&gt;£8,350.00&lt;/a&gt; in today’s money (AUD $15,750).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days QF1/2 is a Airbus A380-800, with a refuel in Dubai. It takes less than 24 hours. And a return Economy airfare can be had for $3,000. A &lt;em&gt;First Class&lt;/em&gt; airfare is $13,500. And First Class in &lt;a href=&quot;http://boardingarea.wpengine.netdna-cdn.com/onemileatatime/files/2013/02/IMG_2188.jpg&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt; is a lot nicer than Economy in the ’50s and ’60s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sydney-to-melbourne&quot;&gt;Sydney to Melbourne&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of us are jet-setting across the world. Sometimes you just need to be at a wedding one state away, and you’d rather not drive for eight hours straight. Fair enough, you’re not alone. The route between Sydney and Melbourne is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World's_busiest_passenger_air_routes&quot;&gt;5th busiest&lt;/a&gt; in the world. Maybe you’re budget concious too, so you’re going to fly ANSETT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you just do a double-take? Yes, ANSETT. It’s 1949, and the flight leaves at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/complete/an49/an49-2.jpg&quot;&gt;3.10 PM&lt;/a&gt;, there will be a stop in Wagga at around 4.30 and you’ll arrive at 6.20 pm (none of this 24 hour nonsense thank you). A return flight costs just £13 (that’s Australian pounds), and it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aussieairliners.org/dc-3/vh-anh/0250.127.html&quot;&gt;Douglas Airliner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rba.gov.au/calculator/annualPreDecimal.html&quot;&gt;$650&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the flight time is an hour and a half, and the cost goes from about $125 return (JetStar) to $450 at peak times (QANTAS). There’s over 90 flights each way per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cathywise.net/images/qantas4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The &amp;quot;QANTAS&amp;quot; Airway: Save Days of Travel by using &amp;quot;Qantas&amp;quot; Mail and Taxi-Planes&quot; /&gt;
[From the collection of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timetableimages.com/ttimages/qantas4.htm&quot;&gt;David Zekria&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2014/01/29/flying-high.html&quot;&gt;Flying High&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on January 29, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello and Welcome]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cathywise.net/2014/01/26/welcome.html" />
  <id>https://cathywise.net/2014/01/26/welcome</id>
  <published>2014-01-26T22:02:10+11:00</published>
  <updated>2014-01-26T22:02:10+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cathy Wise</name>
    <uri>https://cathywise.net</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I plan to use this blog as an opportunity to explore some technical things. Things mostly related to programming, but also perhaps cooking, art, music, craft, politics, economics, religion, or whatever my current interest is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for my collection of cat pictures, quotations, and so on, please see &lt;a href=&quot;http://everbloom.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;my tumblr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net/2014/01/26/welcome.html&quot;&gt;Hello and Welcome&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cathy Wise at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cathywise.net&quot;&gt;Cathy Wise&lt;/a&gt; on January 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>